<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-tram-turn-third-party-authz-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="TURN for 3rd party Authorization ">TURN Extension for Third
    Party Authorization</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>

          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Prashanth Patil" initials="P." surname="Patil">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <street></street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>praspati@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ram Mohan Ravindranath" initials="R."
            surname="Ravindranath">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park,</street>

          <street>Kadabeesanahalli Village, Varthur Hobli,</street>

          <street>Sarjapur-Marathahalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rmohanr@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Justin Uberti" initials="J." surname="Uberti">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>747 6th Ave S</street>

          <street>Kirkland, WA</street>

          <code>98033</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>justin@uberti.name</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>TRAM</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document proposes the use of OAuth to obtain and validate
      ephemeral tokens that can be used for TURN authentication. The usage of
      ephemeral tokens ensure that access to a TURN server can be controlled
      even if the tokens are compromised, as is the case in WebRTC where TURN
      credentials must be specified in Javascript.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>Traversal Using Relay NAT (TURN) TURN <xref target="RFC5766"></xref>
      is a protocol that is often used to improve the connectivity of P2P
      applications. By providing a cloud-based relay service, TURN ensures
      that a connection can be established even when one or both sides is
      incapable of a direct P2P connection. However, as a relay service, it
      imposes a nontrivial cost on the service provider. Therefore, access to
      a TURN service is almost always access-controlled.</t>

      <t>TURN provides a mechanism to control access via "long-term" username/
      password credentials that are provided as part of the TURN protocol. It
      is expected that these credentials will be kept secret; if the
      credentials are discovered, the TURN server could be used by
      unauthorized users or applications. However, in web applications,
      ensuring this secrecy is typically impossible. To address this problem
      and the ones described in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-tram-auth-problems"></xref>, this document proposes the
      use of third party authorization using OAuth for TURN.</t>

      <t>To achieve third party authorization, a resource owner e.g. WebRTC
      server, authorizes a TURN client to access resources on the TURN
      server.</t>

      <t>Using OAuth, a client obtains an ephemeral token from an
      authorization server e.g. WebRTC server, and the token is presented to
      the TURN server instead of the traditional mechanism of presenting
      username/password credentials. The TURN server validates the
      authenticity of the token and provides required services.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="term" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>WebRTC Server: A web server that supports WebRTC <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Access Token: OAuth 2.0 access token.</t>

          <t>mac_key: The session key generated by the authorization server.
          Note that the lifetime of the session key is equal to the lifetime
          of the access token.</t>

          <t>kid: An ephemeral and unique key identifier. The kid also allows
          the resource server to select the appropriate keying material for
          decryption.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="problem_stmt" title="Solution Overview">
      <t>This specification uses the token type 'Assertion' (aka
      self-contained token) described in <xref target="RFC6819"></xref> where
      all the information necessary to authenticate the validity of the token
      is contained within the token itself. This approach has the benefit of
      avoiding a protocol between the TURN server and the authorization server
      for token validation, thus reducing latency. The exact mechanism used by
      a client to obtain a token from the OAuth authorization server is
      outside the scope of this document. For example, a client could make an
      HTTP request to an authorization server to obtain a token that can be
      used to avail TURN services. The TURN token is returned in JSON, along
      with other OAuth Parameters like token type, mac_key, kid, token
      lifetime etc. The client is oblivious to the content of the token. The
      token is embedded within a TURN request sent to the TURN server. Once
      the TURN server has determined the token is valid, TURN services are
      offered for a determined period of time.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="figure1" title="TURN Third Party Authorization">
          <artwork><![CDATA[

+-------------------+                         +--------+  +---------+  
| .........  TURN   |                         |  TURN  |  |  WebRTC |
| .WebRTC .  Client |                         |        |  |         | 
| .Client .         |                         | Server |  |  Server |
| .........         |                         |        |  |         | 
+-------------------+                         +--------+  +---------+
  |       |           Allocate request                |         |
  |       |------------------------------------------>|         |
  |       |                                           |         |
  |       |         Allocate error response           |         |
  |       |<------------------------------------------|         |
  |       |         THIRD-PARTY-AUTHORIZATION         |         |  
  |       |                                           |         |                                      
  |       |                                           |         | 
  |       |      HTTP Request for token               |         |
  |------------------------------------------------------------>|
  |       |      HTTP Response with token parameters  |         |
  |<------------------------------------------------------------|
  |OAuth  |                                           |         |
   Attributes                                         |         |
  |------>|                                           |         |
  |       |    Allocate request ACCESS-TOKEN          |         |
  |       |------------------------------------------>|         |
  |       |                                           |         |
  |       |         Allocate success response         |         |
  |       |<------------------------------------------|         |
  |       |             TURN Messages                 |         |
  |       |      ////// integrity protected //////    |         |
  |       |      ////// integrity protected //////    |         |
  |       |      ////// integrity protected //////    |         |
       ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Note : An implementation may choose to contact the WebRTC server to
      obtain a token even before it makes an allocate request, if it knows the
      server details before hand. For example, once a client has learnt that a
      TURN server supports Third Party authorization from a WebRTC server, the
      client can obtain the token before making subsequent allocate
      requests.</t>

      <t>For example, the client makes the following HTTP request for the
      access token using transport-layer security (with extra line breaks for
      display purposes only):</t>

      <t><figure anchor="Example1" title="Request">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
     POST /o/oauth2/token HTTP/1.1 
     Host: 2001:db8:a000::1
     Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
     timestamp=1361471629
     grant_type=implicit
              ]]></artwork>
        </figure>If the client is authorized then the authorization server
      issues an access token. An example of successful response:</t>

      <figure anchor="Example2" title="Response">
        <preamble></preamble>

        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
     HTTP/1.1 200 OK
     Content-Type: application/json
     Cache-Control: no-store

     {
       "access_token":
"U2FsdGVkX18qJK/kkWmRcnfHglrVTJSpS6yU32kmHmOrfGyI3m1gQj1jRPsr0uBb
HctuycAgsfRX7nJW2BdukGyKMXSiNGNnBzigkAofP6+Z3vkJ1Q5pWbfSRroOkWBn",
       "token_type":"mac",
       "expires_in":1800,
       "kid":"22BIjxU93h/IgwEb",
       "mac_key":"v51N62OM65kyMvfTI08O"
     }
              ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Access token and other attributes issued by the authorization server
      are explained in <xref target="token"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="oauth" title="Obtaining a Token Using OAuth">
      <t>A TURN client should know the authentication capability of the TURN
      server before deciding to use third party authorization with it. A TURN
      client initially makes a request without any authorization. If the TURN
      server supports or mandates third party authorization, it will return an
      error message indicating support for third party authorization. The TURN
      server includes an ERROR-CODE attribute with a value of 401
      (Unauthorized), a nonce value in a NONCE attribute and a SOFTWARE
      attribute that gives information about the TURN server's software. The
      TURN servers also includes additional STUN attribute
      THIRD-PARTY-AUTHORIZATION signaling the TURN client that the TURN server
      supports third party authorization.</t>

      <figure anchor="oauth_webrtc_terminology_map"
              title="OAuth terminology mapped to WebRTC terminology">
        <preamble>The following mapping of OAuth concepts to WebRTC is used
        :</preamble>

        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
              +----------------------+----------------------------+
              |         OAuth        |            WebRTC          |
              +======================+============================+
              | Client               | WebRTC client              |
              +----------------------+----------------------------+
              | Resource owner       | WebRTC server              |
              +----------------------+----------------------------+
              | Authorization server | Authorization server       |
              +----------------------+----------------------------+
              | Resource server      | TURN Server                |
              +----------------------+----------------------------+
              ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Using the OAuth 2.0 authorization framework, a WebRTC client
      (third-party application) obtains limited access to a TURN (resource
      server) on behalf of the WebRTC server (resource owner or authorization
      server). The WebRTC client requests access to resources controlled by
      the resource owner (WebRTC server) and hosted by the resource server
      (TURN server). The WebRTC client obtains access token, lifetime, session
      key (in the mac_key parameter) and key id (kid). The TURN client conveys
      the access token and other OAuth parameters learnt from the
      authorization server to the resource server (TURN server). The TURN
      server obtains the session key from the access token. The TURN server
      validates the token, computes the message integrity of the request and
      takes appropriate action i.e permits the TURN client to create
      allocations. This is shown in an abstract way in <xref
      target="interactions"></xref>.</t>

      <figure anchor="interactions" title="Interactions">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[                        +---------------+
                        |               +<******+
         +------------->| Authorization |       *
         |              | Server        |       *    
         |   +----------|(WebRTC Server)|       *  AS-RS,  
         |   |          |               |       *  AUTH keys    
(2)      |   |           +---------------+      *   (1)
Access   |   |  (3)                             *
Token    |   | Access Token                     *
Request  |   |    +                             *
         |   | Session Key                      *
         |   |                                  *
         |   V                                  V
     +-------+---+                       +-+----=-----+
     |           |         (4)           |            |
     |           | TURN Request + Access |            |
     | WebRTC    | Token                 | TURN       |
     | Client    |---------------------->| Server     |
     | (Alice)   | Allocate Response     |            |
     |           |<----------------------|            |
     +-----------+                       +------------+
                                                  
User : Alice
****: Out-of-Band Long-Term Key Establishment
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>OAuth in <xref target="RFC6749"></xref> defines four grant types.
      This specification uses the OAuth grant type "Implicit" explained in
      section 1.3.2 of <xref target="RFC6749"></xref> where the WebRTC client
      is issued an access token directly. The scope of the access token
      explained in section 3.3 of <xref target="RFC6749"></xref> MUST be
      TURN.</t>

      <section title="Key Establishment">
        <t>The TURN and authorization servers MUST establish a symmetric key
        (K), using an out of band mechanism. Symmetric key MUST be chosen to
        ensure that the size of encrypted token is not large because usage of
        asymmetric keys will result in large encrypted tokens which may not
        fit into a single STUN message. The AS-RS, AUTH keys will be derived
        from K. AS-RS key is used for encrypting the self-contained token and
        message integrity of the encrypted token is calculated using the AUTH
        key. The TURN and authorization servers MUST establish the symmetric
        key over an authenticated secure channel. The establishment of
        symmetric key is outside the scope of this specification. For example,
        implementations could use one of the following mechanisms to establish
        a symmetric key.</t>

        <section anchor="DSKPP" title="DSKPP">
          <t>The two servers could choose to use Dynamic Symmetric Key
          Provisioning Protocol <xref target="RFC6063">(DSKPP)</xref> to
          establish a symmetric key (K). The encryption and MAC algorithms
          will be negotiated using the KeyProvClientHello, KeyProvServerHello
          messages. A unique key identifier (referred to as KeyID) for the
          symmetric key is generated by the DSKPP server (i.e. Authorization
          server) and signalled to the DSKPP client (i.e TURN server) which is
          equivalent to the kid defined in this specification. The AS-RS, AUTH
          keys would be derived from the symmetric key using (HMAC)-based key
          derivation function (HKDF) <xref target="RFC5869">(DSKPP)</xref> and
          the default hash function is SHA-256. For example if the input
          symmetric key (K) is 32 octets length, encryption algorithm is
          AES_128_CBC and HMAC algorithm is HMAC-SHA-256-128 then the
          secondary keys AS-RS, AUTH are generated from the input key K as
          follows</t>

          <t><list style="numbers">
              <t>HKDF-Extract(zero, K) -&gt; PRK</t>

              <t>HKDF-Expand(PRK, zero, 8) -&gt; AS-RS key</t>

              <t>HKDF-Expand(PRK, zero, 16) -&gt; AUTH key</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>NOTE: If Authenticated Encryption with Associated Data (AEAD)
          algorithms <xref target="RFC5116"></xref> specified in <xref
          target="I-D.mcgrew-aead-aes-cbc-hmac-sha2"></xref> are used then
          there is no need to generate the AUTH key.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="HTTP" title="HTTP interactions">
          <t>The two servers could choose to use REST API to establish a
          symmetric key. To retrieve a new symmetric key, the TURN server
          makes an HTTP GET request to the authorization server, specifying
          TURN as the service to allocate the symmetric keys for, and
          optionally specifying the IP Address of the TURN server. The
          response is returned with content-type "application/json", and
          consists of a JSON object containing the symmetric key.</t>

          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[Request
-------

service - specifies the desired service (turn)
myip    - an optional IP address to be associated with the key

example: GET /?service=turn&myip=2001:db8:a000::1


Response
--------

key - Long-term key (K)
ttl - the duration for which the key is valid, in seconds.

example:
{
   "key" : 
"ESIzRFVmd4iZABEiM0RVZgKn6WjLaTC1FXAghRMVTzkBGNaaN496523WIISKerLi",
   "ttl" : 86400,
   "kid" :"22BIjxU93h/IgwEb"
  }]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The AS-RS, AUTH keys are derived from K using HKDF as discussed
          in <xref target="DSKPP"></xref>. Authorization server must also
          signal a unique key identifier (kid) to the TURN server which will
          be used to select the appropriate keying material for decryption.
          The default encryption algorithm to encrypt the self-contained token
          could be Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) in Cipher Block Chaining
          (CBC) mode (AES_128_CBC). The default HMAC algorithm to calculate
          the integrity of the token could be HMAC-SHA-256-128. In this case
          AS-RS key length must be 128-bit, AUTH key length must be 256-bit
          (section 2.6 of <xref target="RFC4868"></xref>).</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Manual" title="Manual provisioning">
          <t>TURN and authorization servers could be manually configured with
          a symmetric key (K) and kid. The default encryption and HMAC
          algorithms could be AES_256_CBC, HMAC-SHA-256-128.</t>

          <t>Note : The mechanisms specified in <xref target="HTTP"></xref>
          <xref target="Manual"></xref> are easy to implement and deploy
          compared to DSKPP but lack encryption and HMAC algorithm
          agility.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Request" title="Forming a Request">
      <t>When a TURN server responds that third party authorization is
      required, a TURN client re-attempts the request, this time including
      access token and kid values in ACCESS-TOKEN and USERNAME STUN
      attributes. The TURN client includes a MESSAGE-INTEGRITY attribute as
      the last attribute in the message over the contents of the TURN message.
      The HMAC for the MESSAGE-INTEGRITY attribute is computed as described in
      section 15.4 of <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> where the mac_key is used
      as the input key for the HMAC computation. The TURN client and server
      will use the mac_key to compute the message integrity and doesn't have
      to perform MD5 hash on the credentials. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="STUN Attributes">
      <t>The following new STUN attributes are introduced by this
      specification to accomplish third party authorization.</t>

      <section anchor="attribute" title="THIRD-PARTY-AUTHORIZATION">
        <t>This attribute is used by the TURN server to inform the client that
        it supports third party authorization. This attribute is used by the
        TURN server to inform the client that it supports third party
        authorization. This optional attribute value be a URL that the client
        should contact, to obtain a token for third party authorization. The
        format for the URL will be as described in <xref
        target="RFC3986"></xref>. The THIRD-PARTY-AUTHORIZATION attribute is a
        comprehension-optional attribute (see Section 15 from <xref
        target="RFC5389"></xref>).</t>

        <t>The TURN server may have tie-up with multiple authorization servers
        so the client MUST provide the TURN server domain name or IP address
        to the authorization server so that it can select the appropriate
        keying material to generate the self-contained token.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="token" title="ACCESS-TOKEN">
        <t>The access token is issued by the authorization server. OAuth does
        not impose any limitation on the length of the access token but if
        path MTU is unknown then STUN messages over IPv4 would need to be less
        than 548 bytes (Section 7.1 of <xref target="RFC5389"></xref>), access
        token length needs to be restricted to fit within the maximum STUN
        message size. Note that the self-contained token is opaque to the
        client and it MUST NOT examine the ticket. The ACCESS-TOKEN attribute
        is a comprehension-optional attribute (see Section 15 from <xref
        target="RFC5389"></xref>).</t>

        <t>The token is structured as follows:</t>

        <t><figure anchor="token1" title="Self-contained token format">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[      struct {
          opaque {
              ushort key_length;
              opaque mac_key[key_length];
              opaque timestamp[8];
              long   lifetime;
          } encrypted_block;
          opaque mac[16];
      } token;
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The fields are described below:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="key_length:">Length of the session key. Key length of
            160-bits MUST be supported (i.e only 160-bit key is used by
            HMAC-SHA-1 for message integrity of STUN message). The key length
            facilitates the hash agility plan discussed in section 16.3 of
            <xref target="RFC5389"></xref>.</t>

            <t hangText="mac_key:">The session key generated by the
            authorization server.</t>

            <t hangText="Timestamp:">64-bit unsigned integer field containing
            a timestamp. The value indicates the time since January 1, 1970,
            00:00 UTC, by using a fixed point format. In this format, the
            integer number of seconds is contained in the first 48 bits of the
            field, and the remaining 16 bits indicate the number of 1/64K
            fractions of a second (Native format - Unix).</t>

            <t hangText="Lifetime:">The lifetime of the access token, in
            seconds. For example, the value 3600 indicates one hour. The
            Lifetime value SHOULD be equal to the "expires_in" parameter
            defined in section 4.2.2 of <xref target="RFC6749"></xref>.</t>

            <t hangText="mac:">The Hashed Message Authentication Code (HMAC)
            is calculated with AUTH key over the encrypted portion of the
            token (encrypted_block). Thus encryption is applied before
            authentication on the sender side and conversely on the receiver
            side.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The token MUST be encoded as defined in Section 4 of <xref
        target="RFC4648"></xref> and then encrypted using the symmetric
        long-term key established between the resource server and the
        authorization server, as shown in <xref target="interactions"></xref>
        as AS-RS key. Since the access token is valid for a specific period of
        time the resource server MUST cache it so that it need not to be
        provided in every request within an existing allocation. The access
        token can be re-used for multiple Allocate requests to the same TURN
        server. The TURN client MUST include the ACCESS-TOKEN attribute only
        in Allocate and Refresh requests.</t>

        <t>Note : If Authenticated Encryption with Associated Data (AEAD)
        algorithm specified in <xref
        target="I-D.mcgrew-aead-aes-cbc-hmac-sha2"></xref> are used then there
        is no need to explicitly compute HMAC. In this scenario the mac field
        must carry the initialization vector (IV).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Response"
             title="Receiving a request with ACCESS-TOKEN attribute">
      <t>The TURN server, on receiving a request with ACCESS-TOKEN attribute,
      performs checks listed in section 10.2.2 of <xref
      target="RFC5389"></xref> in addition to the following steps to verify
      that the access token is valid:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>TURN server selects the keying material based on kid signalled in
          the USERNAME attribute.</t>

          <t>It performs the verification of the token message integrity by
          calculating calculates HMAC over the encrypted_block in the
          self-contained token using AUTH key and if the resulting value does
          not match the mac field in the self-contained token then it rejects
          the request with an error response 401 (Unauthorized). If AEAD
          algorithm is used then this step is skipped.</t>

          <t>TURN server obtains the mac_key by retrieving the content of the
          access token (which requires decryption of the self-contained token
          using the AS-RS key).</t>

          <t>The TURN server verifies that no replay took place by performing
          the following check: <list style="symbols">
              <t> The access token is accepted if the timestamp field in the
              self-contained token (TS) is recent enough to the reception time
              of the TURN request (RDnew) using the following formula:
              Lifetime + Delta &gt; abs(RDnew - TS). The RECOMMENDED value for
              the allowed Delta is 5 seconds. If the timestamp is NOT within
              the boundaries then the TURN server discards the request with
              error response 401 (Unauthorized).</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The TURN server uses the mac_key to compute the message integrity
          over the request and if the resulting value does not match the
          contents of the MESSAGE-INTEGRITY attribute then it rejects the
          request with an error response 401 (Unauthorized).</t>

          <t>If all the checks pass, the TURN server continues to process the
          request. Any response generated by the server MUST include the
          MESSAGE-INTEGRITY attribute, computed using the mac_key.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The lifetime provided by the TURN server in the Allocate and Refresh
      responses MUST be less than or equal to the lifetime of the token.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="client" title="Changes to TURN Client">
      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A TURN response is discarded by the client if the value computed
          for message integrity using mac_key does not match the contents of
          the MESSAGE-INTEGRITY attribute.</t>

          <t>If the access token expires then the client MUST obtain a new
          token from the authorization server and use it for new allocations.
          The client MUST also use the new token to refresh existing
          allocations. This way client has to maintain only one token per TURN
          server.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>When OAuth is used the interaction between the client and the
      authorization server requires Transport Layer Security (TLS) with a
      ciphersuite offering confidentiality protection. The session key MUST
      NOT be transmitted in clear since this would completely destroy the
      security benefits of the proposed scheme. If an attacker tries to replay
      message with ACCESS-TOKEN attribute then the server can detect that the
      transaction id was used for an old request and thus prevent the replay
      attack.</t>

      <t>Security considerations discussed in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2-http-mac"></xref> and <xref
      target="RFC5766"></xref> are to be taken into account.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to add the following attributes to the <xref
      target="iana-stun">STUN attribute registry</xref>, <list style="symbols">
          <t>THIRD-PARTY-AUTHORIZATION</t>

          <t>ACCESS-TOKEN</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Authors would like to thank Dan Wing, Pal Martinsen and Oleg
      Moskalenko for comments and review. The authors would like to give
      special thanks to Brandon Williams for his help.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6749"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3986"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4648"
include="reference.RFC.6063"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4868"?>

      <reference anchor="iana-stun"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/stun-parameters/stun-pa rameters.xml">
        <front>
          <title>IANA: STUN Attributes</title>

          <author fullname="IANA" surname="IANA">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview' ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-tram-auth-problems'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-v2-http-mac'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.mcgrew-aead-aes-cbc-hmac-sha2'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5766"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6819"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6063"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5116"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5869"?>

      <!---->
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
