<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline ="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-wing-tsvwg-turn-flowdata-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="TURN flowdata">TURN extension to convey flow
    characteristics</title>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D" surname="Wing">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>821 Alder Drive</street>

          <city>Milpitas</city>

          <region>California</region>

          <code>95035</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>

          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Brandon Williams" initials="B." surname="Williams">
      <organization>Akamai, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>8 Cambridge Center</street>

          <city>Cambridge, MA</city>

          <code>02142</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>brandon.williams@akamai.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ram Mohan Ravindranath" initials="R"
            surname="Ravindranath">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park</street>

          <street>Sarjapur-Marathahalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rmohanr@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>TSVWG</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>TURN server and the network in which it is hosted due to load could
      adversely impact the traffic relayed through it. During such high load
      event, it is desirable to shed some traffic but TURN server lack
      requirements about the flows to prioritize them. This document defines
      such a mechanism to communicate flow characteristics from the TURN
      client to its TURN server.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Traversal Using Relay NAT (TURN) <xref target="RFC5766"></xref> is a
      protocol that is often used to improve the connectivity of P2P
      applications. TURN allows a connection to be established when one or
      both sides is incapable of a direct P2P connection. A TURN server could
      be provided by an enterprise network, an access network, an application
      service provider or a third party provider. A TURN server could be used
      to relay media streams, WebRTC data channels <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview"></xref> , gaming, file transfer etc. A
      TURN server and the network in which it is hosted could have
      insufficient bandwidth or other characteristics that could adversely
      impact the traffic relayed through it and need a mechanism to identify
      and provide differentiated service to flows relayed through the TURN
      server.</t>

      <t>This specification provides a mechanism for the client to signal the
      flow characteristics of a relay channel to the TURN server, so that
      certain relay channels can receive service that is differentiated from
      others. The TURN server authorizes the request and signals back to the
      client that it can (fully or partially) accommodate the flow. This sort
      of signaling will be useful for long-lived flows such as media streams,
      WebRTC data channels etc traversing through the TURN server. The TURN
      server can further communicate the flow information to a number of
      on-path devices in its network using a Policy decision Point (e.g. SDN
      controller). This way the network hosting the TURN server can
      accommodate the flow. With this mechanism, a TURN client can request the
      TURN server to provide certain characteristics for the relayed channel
      on both legs (client-to-server, server-to-peer). Applications using TURN
      as a communication relay would benefit from such an arrangement as it
      would improve the Quality of Experience (QOE) of the end user.</t>

      <t>Note: It is not the intent of this document to advocate in favor of
      prioritizing relayed candidates over host, server-reflexive candidates,
      but to highlight the proposed mechanism only when TURN server is
      selected for various reasons like privacy, ICE connectivity checks with
      local host/server-reflexive candidates have failed etc.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-term" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="design" title="Design considerations">
      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>TURN client can choose to either use Send and Data indications or
          channels to exchange data with its peer. For bandwidth intensive
          applications (like video, audio, WebRTC data channels) using Send
          indication or Data indication adds 36 bytes overhead to the
          application data and substantially increases the bandwidth required
          between the client and the server. Hence channels are commonly used
          for bandwidth intensive applications to exchange data. The other
          problem with using Send/Data indications is that if the TURN server
          determines that a flow can only be partially accommodated then this
          feedback cannot be conveyed back to the client. Hence in this
          specification focuses on conveying the flow characteristics only in
          ChannelBind request/response.</t>

          <t>DSCP style markings can also help provide QOS, but has the
          following limitations: <list style="symbols">
              <t>DiffServ style packet marking can help provide QoS in some
              environments but DSCP markings are often modified or removed at
              various points in the network or when crossing network
              boundaries. DSCP markings set by the client may be modified or
              removed by the intervening network(s) before it reaches the TURN
              server.</t>

              <t>DSCP values are site specific, with each site selecting its
              own code points for each QoS level, hence it may not work across
              domains. However <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rtcweb-qos"></xref> recommends default
              set of DSCP values for browsers when there is no site specific
              information.</t>

              <t>TURN client may not be able to set DSCP values for outgoing
              packets because of OS limitations.</t>

              <t>DSCP provides differentiated service only in the outgoing
              direction of a flow.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The mechanism described in this document has none of the above
      limitations and the following useful properties:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Usable at the application level to the TURN client, without
          needing operating system support.</t>

          <t>Robust metadata support, to convey sufficient information to the
          TURN server about the flow.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Solution Overview">
      <t>When a channel binding is initiated by the client, it may also
      indicate certain characteristics of its flow to the TURN server. The
      TURN server uses that information to prioritize the flow in its network
      and signals back to the client that it can fully or partially
      accommodate the flow.</t>

      <t>This specification defines one new comprehension-optional STUN
      attribute: FLOWDATA. If a TURN client wishes to signal the flow
      characteristics of the relay channel it MUST insert this attribute in
      ChannelBind request. This attribute if used MUST be sent only in the
      ChannelBind request. Other specifications in future may extend this
      attribute to be used in other STUN methods. The TURN server determines
      if it can accommodate that flow, making configuration changes if
      necessary to accommodate the flow, and returns information in the
      FLOWDATA attribute indicating its ability to accommodate the described
      flow.</t>

      <section title="Sending a ChannelBind Request">
        <t>The TURN client sends ChannelBind request with the FLOWDATA STUN
        attribute to signal the flow characteristics of the relay channel to
        the TURN server. If the flow characteristics of a relay channel change
        then the client MAY send ChannelBind request with an updated FLOWDATA
        STUN attribute to refresh the binding. Similarly if the binding is
        refreshed using ChannelBind request then the client can also signal
        updated FLOWDATA STUN attribute if the flow characteristics of the
        relay channel have changed.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Receiving a ChannelBind Request">
        <t>When a TURN server receives a ChannelBind request that includes a
        FLOWDATA attribute, it processes the request as per the TURN
        specification <xref target="RFC5766"></xref> plus the specific rules
        mentioned below.</t>

        <t>The TURN server will determine if it can provide the flow resources
        requested by the client. If the TURN server determines the flow can
        only be fully or partially accommodated, it returns values in the
        FLOWDATA fields that it can accommodate or returns 0 in those FLOWDATA
        fields where it has no information. In other words if the request
        indicated a low tolerance for delay but the TURN server determines
        that only high delay is available, the FLOWDATA response indicates
        high delay is available. The same sort of processing occurs on all of
        the FLOWDATA fields of the response (upstream and downstream delay
        tolerance, loss tolerance, jitter tolerance, minimum bandwidth,
        maximum bandwidth). If the TURN server determines the flow can only be
        partially accommodated and the client has also signaled CHECK-
        ALTERNATE attribute <xref target="I-D.williams-peer-redirect"></xref>
        then the TURN server MAY re-direct the client to an alternate TURN
        server that could accommodate the flow characteristics conveyed by the
        client.</t>

        <t>If the TURN server can accommodate the flow as described in the
        FLOWDATA attribute, it sends a success response and includes the
        FLOWDATA attribute filled in according to <xref
        target="FLOWDATA"></xref>. The TURN server SHOULD include the FLOWDATA
        attribute in ChannelBind response only when the client had signaled
        FLOWDATA attribute in ChannelBind request.</t>

        <section title="Conflict Resolution">
          <t>It is possible that two hosts send requests with different
          thresholds for delay or jitter in each direction for the same flow,
          and their requests arrive at the same TURN server. If this occurs,
          it is RECOMMENDED that the TURN server uses the stricter delay/loss
          tolerance (that is, the lower tolerance to delay or jitter). The
          diagram below depicts a conflict message flow.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="conflict"
              title="Message diagram, resolving conflict">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   
TURN Client A             TURN server           TURN Client B
     |                         |                       |
     |-loss=med, delay=med---->|<-loss=hi, delay=hi----|
     |                         |                       |
     |                    (conflict!)                  |
     |                         |                       |
     |                         |--loss=med, delay=med->|
     |                         |                       |
     |<--loss=med, delay=med---|                       |

]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>In the above example if the TURN server has already responded to
          client B before it receives the request from client A then the TURN
          server can correct the conflict only when the client B refreshes the
          binding.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Receiving a ChannelBind Response">
        <t>When the client receives a ChannelBind success response, it
        proceeds with processing the response according to the TURN
        specification <xref target="RFC5766"></xref>. If the message does not
        include an FLOWDATA attribute, no additional processing is required.
        The returned FLOWDATA attribute, if present, indicates the
        accommodation of this flow the TURN server will perform. This document
        does not define what the TURN client might do with that information,
        but it could choose among several TURN servers or use it for other
        purposes.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="FLOWDATA" title="FLOWDATA format">
      <t>This section describes the format of the new STUN attribute FLOWDATA.
      FLOWDATA will have a type TBD-CA and length of 4 bytes. The FLOWDATA
      attribute in the request has the following format.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="Figure1" title="FLOWDATA attribute in request">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | Attribute Type (TBD-CA)   |          Length (4)               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | uDT | uLT | uJT |   RSVD1     | dDT | dLT | dJT |    RSVD2    |
  +---------------------------------------------------------------+
  |                  Upstream Minimum Bandwidth                   |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                 Downstream Minimum Bandwidth                  |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                  Upstream Maximum Bandwidth                   |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                 Downstream Maximum Bandwidth                  |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Description of the fields:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="uDT:">Upstream Delay Tolerance, 0=no information
          available, 1=very low, 2=low, 3=medium, 4=high.</t>

          <t hangText="uLT:">Upstream Loss Tolerance, 0=no information
          available, 1=very low, 2=low, 3=medium, 4=high.</t>

          <t hangText="uJT:">Upstream Jitter Tolerance, 0=no information
          available, 1=very low, 2=low, 3=medium, 4=high.</t>

          <t hangText="RSVD1:">Reserved (7 bits), MUST be ignored on reception
          and MUST be 0 on transmission.</t>

          <t hangText="dDT:">Downstream Delay Tolerance, 0=no information
          available, 1=very low, 2=low, 3=medium, 4=high.</t>

          <t hangText="dLT:">Downstream Loss Tolerance, 0=no information
          available, 1=very low, 2=low, 3=medium, 4=high.</t>

          <t hangText="dJT:">Downstream Jitter Tolerance, 0=no information
          available, 1=very low, 2=low, 3=medium, 4=high.</t>

          <t hangText="RSVD2:">Reserved (7 bits), MUST be ignored on reception
          and MUST be 0 on transmission.</t>

          <t hangText="Upstream Minimum Bandwidth:">Measures bandwidth sent by
          the client. Value is in octets per second. The value 0 means no
          information is available.</t>

          <t hangText="Downstream Minimum Bandwidth:">Measures bandwidth sent
          to the client. Value is in octets per second. The value 0 means no
          information is available.</t>

          <t hangText="Upstream Maximum Bandwidth:">Measures bandwidth sent by
          the client. Value is in octets per second. The value 0 means no
          information is available.</t>

          <t hangText="Downstream Maximum Bandwidth:">Measures bandwidth sent
          to the client. Value is in octets per second. The value 0 means no
          information is available.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Different applications have different needs for their flows. The
      following table is derived from <xref target="RFC4594"></xref> to serve
      as a guideline for tolerance to loss, delay and jitter for some sample
      applications. The range 0 to 4 used for the fields in FLOWDATA
      attribute, meets the need to convey the tolerance levels for the traffic
      serviced by the service classes in the below table.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="Figure2" title="Flow characteristics">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

 -------------------------------------------------------------------
|Service Class  |                              |    Tolerance to    |
|    Name       |  Traffic Characteristics     | Loss |Delay |Jitter|
|===============+==============================+======+======+======|
|   Network     |Variable size packets, mostly |      |      |      |
|   Control     |inelastic short messages, but |  Low |  Low | High |
|               | traffic can also burst       |      |      |      |
|               | (e.g., OSPF)                 |      |      |      |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
|               | Fixed-size small packets,    | Very | Very | Very |
|  Telephony    | constant emission rate,      |  Low |  Low |  Low |
|               | inelastic and low-rate flows |      |      |      |
|               | (e.g., G.711, G.729)         |      |      |      |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
|   Signaling   | Variable size packets, some  | Low  | Low  | High |
|               | what bursty short-lived flows|      |      |      |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
|  Multimedia   | Variable size packets,       | Low  | Very |      |
| Conferencing  | constant transmit interval,  |  -   | Low  | Low  |
|               |rate adaptive, reacts to loss |Medium|      |      |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
|   Real-Time   | RTP/UDP streams, inelastic,  | Low  | Very | Low  |
|  Interactive  | mostly variable rate         |      | Low  |      |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
|  Multimedia   |  Variable size packets,      |Low - |Medium| High |
|   Streaming   | elastic with variable rate   |Medium|      |      |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
|   Broadcast   | Constant and variable rate,  | Very |Medium| Low  |
|     Video     | inelastic, non-bursty flows  |  Low |      |      |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
|  Low-Latency  | Variable rate, bursty short- | Low  |Low - | High |
|      Data     |  lived elastic flows         |      |Medium|      |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
|      OAM      |  Variable size packets,      | Low  |Medium| High |
|               |  elastic & inelastic flows   |      |      |      |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
|High-Throughput| Variable rate, bursty long-  | Low  |Medium| High |
|      Data     |   lived elastic flows        |      |- High|      |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
|   Standard    | A bit of everything          |   0     0       0  |
|---------------+------------------------------+------+------+------|
| Low-Priority  | Non-real-time and elastic    | High | High | High |
|      Data     | (e.g., network backup)       |      |      |      |
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
   
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The FLOWDATA attribute in the response has the following format</t>

      <t><figure anchor="Figure3" title="FLOWDATA attribute in response">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | Attribute Type (TBD-CA)   |          Length (4)               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | AuDT| AuLT| AuJT|   RSVD1     | AdDT| AdLT| AdJT|    RSVD2    |
  +---------------------------------------------------------------+
  |            Accommodated Upstream Minimum Bandwidth            |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |           Accommodated Downstream Minimum Bandwidth           |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |            Accommodated Upstream Maximum Bandwidth            |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |           Accommodated Downstream Maximum Bandwidth           |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>Description of the fields:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="AuDT:">Accommodated Upstream Delay Tolerance, 0=no
          information available, 1=able to accommodate very low, 2=able to
          accommodate low, 3=able to accommodate medium, 4=able to accommodate
          high.</t>

          <t hangText="AuLT:">Accommodated Upstream Loss Tolerance, 0=no
          information available, 1=able to accommodate very low, 2=able to
          accommodate low, 3=able to accommodate medium, 4=able to accommodate
          high.</t>

          <t hangText="AuJT:">Accommodated Upstream Jitter Tolerance, 0=no
          information available, 1=able to accommodate very low, 2=able to
          accommodate low, 3=able to accommodate medium, 4=able to accommodate
          high.</t>

          <t hangText="RSVD1:">Reserved (7 bits), MUST be ignored on reception
          and MUST be 0 on transmission.</t>

          <t hangText="AdDT:">Accommodated Downstream Delay Tolerance, 0=no
          information available, 1=able to accommodate very low, 2=able to
          accommodate low, 3=able to accommodate medium, 4=able to accommodate
          high.</t>

          <t hangText="AdLT:">Accommodated Downstream Loss Tolerance, 0=no
          information available, 1=able to accommodate very low, 2=able to
          accommodate low, 3=able to accommodate medium, 4=able to accommodate
          high.</t>

          <t hangText="AdJT:">Accommodated Downstream Jitter Tolerance, 0=no
          information available, 1=able to accommodate very low, 2=able to
          accommodate low, 3=able to accommodate medium, 4=able to accommodate
          high.</t>

          <t hangText="RSVD2:">Reserved (7 bits), MUST be ignored on reception
          and MUST be 0 on transmission.</t>

          <t hangText="Accommodated Upstream Minimum Bandwidth:">Bandwidth
          accommodated for this flow. Value in bytes per second. 0 means no
          information is available.</t>

          <t hangText="Accommodated Downstream Minimum Bandwidth:">Bandwidth
          accommodated for this flow. Value in bytes per second. 0 means no
          information is available.</t>

          <t hangText="Accommodated Upstream Maximum Bandwidth:">Bandwidth
          accommodated for this flow. Value in bytes per second. 0 means no
          information is available.</t>

          <t hangText="Accommodated Downstream Maximum Bandwidth:">Bandwidth
          accommodated for this flow Value in bytes per second, 0 means no
          information is available.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>On some networks, only certain users or certain applications are
      authorized to signal the priority of a flow. This authorization can be
      achieved with STUN long-term authentication <xref
      target="RFC5389"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec.iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document defines the FLOWDATA STUN attribute, described in <xref
      target="FLOWDATA"></xref>. IANA has allocated the comprehension-optional
      codepoint TBD-CA for this attribute.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t>Authors would like to thank Anca Zamfir and Charles Eckel for their
      comments and review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5766"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-overview"  ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.williams-peer-redirect" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rtcweb-qos"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4594"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
