<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-tram-stun-path-data-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="STUN Path Characteristics">Discovery of path
    characteristics using STUN</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>

          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>California</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paal-Erik Martinsen" initials="P.E" surname="Martinsen">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Philip Pedersens vei 22</street>

          <city>Lysaker</city>

          <region>Akershus</region>

          <code>1325</code>

          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>

        <email>palmarti@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>TRAM</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>A host with multiple interfaces needs to choose the best interface
      for communication. Oftentimes, this decision is based on a static
      configuration and does not consider the path characteristics, which may
      affect the user experience.</t>

      <t>This document describes a mechanism for an endpoint to find the path
      characteristics using Session Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN). This
      information can be used to influence endpoint's Interactive Connectivity
      Establishment (ICE) candidate pair selection algorithm.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>ICE <xref target="RFC5245"></xref> uses a prioritization formula to
      perform connectivity checks, in which the most preferred address pairs
      are tested first and when a sufficiently good pair is discovered, that
      pair is used for communications and ICE connectivity tests are stopped.
      This approach works well for an endpoint with a single interface, but is
      too simplistic for endpoints with multiple interfaces. ICE connectivity
      checks can be used measure the path characteristics but the problem is
      that STUN responses from re-transmitted requests are
      indistinguishable.</t>

      <t>This draft extends STUN <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> to distinguish
      STUN responses from re-transmitted requests and helps client determine
      path characteristics like round-trip time (RTT) and packet loss in each
      direction, which can be used by the controlling agent to influence the
      ICE candidate pair priority and relayed candidates priority .</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Notational Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This note uses terminology defined in <xref
      target="RFC5245">ICE</xref> and STUN <xref target="RFC5389"></xref>
      .</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="alg_over"
             title="Path characteristics determination mechanism">
      <t>When multiple paths are available for communication, the first
      approach is to send an ICE connectivity check across each path and
      choose the path with the best round trip time. Choosing the path with
      the best round trip time is a reasonable approach, but re-transmits can
      cause an otherwise-good path to appear flawed. However, STUN's
      retransmission algorithm <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> cannot determine
      the round-trip time if a STUN packet is re-transmitted, because each
      packet retransmission is identical. To resolve that, this document
      changes that retransmission behavior for idempotent packets. In addition
      to determining RTT, it is also desirable to detect which path direction
      caused packet loss, described as "bi-directional path characteristics,"
      below. This is achieved by defining a new STUN attribute and requiring
      compliant STUN (TURN, ICE) servers to count retransmitted request
      packets. </t>

      <t>This specification defines a new comprehension-optional STUN
      attribute PATH-CHARACTERISTIC. PATH-CHARACTERISTIC will have a STUN Type
      TBD-CA. This type is in the comprehension-optional range, which means
      that STUN agents can safely ignore the attribute if they do not
      understand it.</t>

      <t>If a client wishes to determine the path characteristics then it
      inserts PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in STUN request. In
      PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute client sends the number of times the STUN
      request is retransmitted with the same Transaction ID. The server would
      echo back the retransmission count in the response so that client can
      distinguish STUN responses from re-transmitted requests. Client can thus
      use STUN requests and responses to calculate the round-trip time (RTT).
      The server MAY also convey number of times it received the request with
      the same Transaction ID and number of responses it has sent for the STUN
      request to the client. This information can be used by the client to
      determine packet loss in each direction.</t>

      <section title="The PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in request">
        <t>The PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in the request takes a 1-byte
        Value, which means that the Length is 1 and 3 bytes of padding are
        required after the value. When sending a STUN request, the
        PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute allows a client to indicate to the
        server that it wants to determine path characteristics. If the client
        receives a STUN response with error code 420 (Unknown Attribute) and
        PATH-CHARACTERISTIC is listed in the UNKNOWN-ATTRIBUTE attribute of
        the message, the client SHOULD retransmit the original request without
        the PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute. However this case is not expected
        due to the use of a comprehension-optional attribute type.</t>

        <t>This specification changes one the STUN message structuring rules
        explained in section 6 of <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> that resends
        of the same request as usual reuse the same transaction ID, ReTransCnt
        in PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute will be incremented by 1 for every
        re-transmission and the re-transmitted STUN request MUST be bit-wise
        identical to the previous request except for the ReTransCnt value.</t>

        <t>The format of the value in PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in the
        request is:</t>

        <t><figure anchor="Figure1"
            title=" PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in request">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[         0
         0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        | ReTransCnt    |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The field is described below:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="ReTransCnt:">Number of times request is
            re-transmitted with the same transaction ID to the server.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="The PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in response">
        <t>When a server receives a STUN request that includes a
        PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute, it processes the request as per the
        STUN specification <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> plus the specific
        rules mentioned here. The server checks the following:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>If the PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute is not recognized, ignore
            the attribute because its type indicates that it is comprehension-
            optional. This should be the existing behavior as explained in
            section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC5389"></xref>.</t>

            <t>The server that supports PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute MUST
            echo back ReTransCnt in the response.</t>

            <t>If the server is stateless or does not want to remember the
            transaction ID then it would populate value 0 for the ReqTransCnt
            and RespTransCnt fields in PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute sent in
            the response .If the server is stateful then it populates
            ReqTransCnt with the number of times it received the STUN request
            with the same transaction ID and RespTransCnt with the number of
            responses it has sent for the STUN request.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><figure anchor="Figure2"
            title=" PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in response">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[       0                   1                   2                   3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|        TransCnt               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |   ReqTransCnt                 |        RespTransCnt           |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The fields are described below:<list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="TransCnt:">Copied from request.</t>

            <t hangText="ReqTransCnt:">Number of times request is received
            from the client with the same transaction ID.</t>

            <t hangText="RespTransCnt:">Number of responses sent to the client
            for the same transaction ID.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="mif" title="Multiple Interfaces and other usecases">
      <t>The STUN attribute defined in this specification can be used by
      applications in the following scenarios:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>When an endpoint has multiple interfaces (for example 3G, 4G,
          WiFi, VPN, etc.), an ICE agent can choose the interfaces for media
          streams according to the path characteristics. After STUN responses
          to STUN checks are received, the ICE agent using regular nomination
          can sort the ICE candidate pairs according to the path
          characteristics discovered using STUN. The controlling agent can
          assign highest priority to candidate pair which best fulfills the
          desired path characteristics.</t>

          <t>[TODO: Add details of
          http://juberti.github.io/draughts/nombis/draft-uberti-mmusic-nombis.html
          that explains simplifying and improving the procedures for candidate
          nomination in ICE to make dynamic decisions.]</t>

          <t>When a host has multiple interfaces available an MPRTP
          application can choose the interface for the primary subflow and
          interfaces for subsequent subflows according to the path
          characteristics discovered using STUN.</t>

          <t>The STUN extension proposed in this specification can also be
          used to choose a TURN server that provides the best user experience
          (section 3.1 of <xref
          target="I-D.patil-tram-turn-serv-selection"></xref>).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>[Paragraphs in braces should be removed by the RFC Editor upon
      publication]</t>

      <t>[The PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute requires that IANA allocate a
      value in the "STUN attributes Registry" from the comprehension-optional
      range (0x8000-0xFFFF), to be replaced for TBD-CA throughout this
      document]</t>

      <t>This document defines the PATH-CHARACTERISTIC STUN attribute,
      described in <xref target="alg_over"></xref>. IANA has allocated the
      comprehension-optional codepoint TBD-CA for this attribute.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations discussed in <xref target="RFC5389"></xref>
      are to be taken into account. STUN requires the 96 bits transaction ID
      to be uniformly and randomly chosen from the interval 0 .. 2**96-1, and
      be cryptographically strong. This is good enough security against an
      off-path attacker. An on-path attacker can either inject a fake response
      or modify the values in PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute to mislead the
      client and server, this attack can be mitigated using STUN
      authentication. As PATH-CHARACTERISTIC is expected to be used between
      peers using ICE, and ICE uses STUN short-term credential mechanism the
      risk of on-path attack influencing the messages is minimal. However, an
      attacker could corrupt, remove, or delay an ICE request or response, in
      order to discourage that path from being used. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TODO</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5245"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"  ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.patil-tram-turn-serv-selection'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
