<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-tram-stun-path-data-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="STUN Path Characteristics">Discovery of path
    characteristics using STUN</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>

          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>California</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paal-Erik Martinsen" initials="P.E" surname="Martinsen">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Philip Pedersens vei 22</street>

          <city>Lysaker</city>

          <region>Akershus</region>

          <code>1325</code>

          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>

        <email>palmarti@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Varun Singh" initials="V." surname="Singh">
      <organization abbrev="callstats.io">Nemu Dialogue System
      Oy</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Espoo</city>

          <code>02235</code>

          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>varun@callstats.io</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>TRAM</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes how to extend Session Traversal
      Utilities for NAT (STUN) to measure the transaction RTT and
      count lost transaction packets.  This information can be used by
      Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE) to improve the
      active path selection.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>This draft extends STUN <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> to
      distinguish STUN responses to re-transmitted requests and
      assists the client in determining the path characteristics
      round-trip time (RTT) and packet loss in each direction between
      endpoints.</t>
      
      <t>When measuring RTT on stun requests re-transmits can cause an
      otherwise-good path to appear flawed. However, STUN's
      retransmission algorithm <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> cannot
      determine the round-trip time if a STUN request packet is
      re-transmitted, because each packet request and retransmission
      is identical.
      </t>

      <t>To resolve the issue of identical request and response
      packets in a STUN transaction, this document changes that
      retransmission behavior for idempotent packets. In addition to
      determining RTT, it is also desirable to detect which path
      direction caused packet loss, described as "bi-directional path
      characteristics," below. This is achieved by defining a new STUN
      attribute and requires compliant STUN (TURN, ICE) servers to
      count retransmitted request packets.</t>
  
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Notational Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This note uses terminology defined in <xref
      target="RFC5245">ICE</xref> and STUN <xref target="RFC5389"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="alg_over"
             title="Path characteristics determination mechanism">
      
      <t>This specification defines a new comprehension-optional STUN
      attribute PATH-CHARACTERISTIC. PATH-CHARACTERISTIC will have a STUN Type
      TBD-CA. This type is in the comprehension-optional range, which means
      that STUN agents can safely ignore the attribute if they do not
      understand it.</t>

      <t>If a client wishes to determine the path characteristics, it inserts
      the PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in a STUN request. In the
      PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute client sends the number of times the STUN
      request is retransmitted with the same Transaction ID. The server would
      echo back the retransmission count in the response so that client can
      distinguish STUN responses from the re-transmitted requests. Hence, the
      endpoint can use the STUN requests and responses to determine the
      round-trip time (RTT). The server may also convey the number of times it
      received the request with the same Transaction ID and the number of
      responses it has sent for the STUN request to the client. Further, this
      information enables the client to determine packet loss in each
      direction.</t>

      <section title="The PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in request">
        <t>The PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in a STUN request takes a 1-byte
        Value, which means that the Length is 1 and 3 bytes of padding are
        required after the value (Section 15 of <xref
        target="RFC5389"></xref>). When sending a STUN request, the
        PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute allows a client to indicate to the
        server that it wants to determine path characteristics. If the client
        receives a STUN response with error code 420 (Unknown Attribute) and
        PATH-CHARACTERISTIC is listed in the UNKNOWN-ATTRIBUTE attribute of
        the message, the client SHOULD retransmit the original request without
        the PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute. However this case is not expected
        to occur, due to the use of the comprehension-optional attribute
        type.</t>

        <t>This specification updates one the STUN message structuring rules
        explained in Section 6 of <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> that resends
        of the same request reuse the same transaction ID and are bit-wise
        identical to the previous request. The ReTransCnt in the
        PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute will be incremented by 1 for every
        re-transmission and the re-transmitted STUN request MUST be bit-wise
        identical to the previous request except for the ReTransCnt value.</t>

        <t>The format of the value in PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in the
        request is:</t>

        <t><figure anchor="Figure1"
            title=" PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in request">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[         0
         0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        | ReTransCnt    |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The field is described below:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="ReTransCnt:">Number of times request is
            re-transmitted with the same transaction ID to the server.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="The PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in response">
        <t>When a server receives a STUN request that includes a
        PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute, it processes the request as per the
        STUN specification <xref target="RFC5389"></xref> plus the specific
        rules mentioned here. The server checks the following:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>If the PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute is not recognized, ignore
            the attribute because its type indicates that it is comprehension-
            optional. This should be the existing behavior as explained in
            section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC5389"></xref>.</t>

            <t>The server that supports PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute MUST
            echo back ReTransCnt in the response.</t>

            <t>If the server is stateless or does not want to remember the
            transaction ID then it would populate value 0 for the ReqTransCnt
            and RespTransCnt fields in PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute sent in
            the response .If the server is stateful then it populates
            ReqTransCnt with the number of times it received the STUN request
            with the same transaction ID and RespTransCnt with the number of
            responses it has sent for the STUN request.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><figure anchor="Figure2"
            title=" PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute in response">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|        ReTransCnt             |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |   ReqTransCnt                 |        RespTransCnt           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The fields are described below:<list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="ReTransCnt:">Copied from request.</t>

            <t hangText="ReqTransCnt:">Number of times request is received
            from the client with the same transaction ID.</t>

            <t hangText="RespTransCnt:">Number of responses sent to the client
            for the same transaction ID.</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="Example Operation">
          <t>The operation is described in <xref target="Figure3"></xref>. In
          the first case, all the requests and responses are received
          correctly. In the upstream loss case, the first request is lost, but
          the second one is received correctly, the client on receiving the
          response notes that while 2 requests were sent, only one was
          received by the server, also the server realizes that the
          RespTransCnt does not match the ReTransCnt, therefore 1 request was
          lost. This may also occur at startup in the presence firewalls or
          NATs that block unsolicited incoming traffic. In the downstream loss
          case, the responses get lost, client expecting multiple response
          notes that while the server responded to 3 requests but only 1
          response was received. In the both loss case, requests and responses
          get lost in tandem, the server notes one request packet was not
          received, while the client expecting 3 responses received only one,
          it notes that one request and response packets were lost.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="Figure3"
              title="Retransmit Operation between client and Server">
              <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[ 
    Normal     |  Upstream loss  |  Downstream loss|      Both loss  |
Client  Server |  Client  Server |  Client  Server |  Client  Server |
-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-|
1         1,1  |  1         x    |  1         1,1  |  1         x    |
  1,1          |                 |    x            |                 |
2         2,2  |  2         2,1  |  2         2,2  |  2         2,1  |
  2,2          |    2,1          |    x            |    x            |
3         3,3  |  3         3,2  |  3         3,3  |  3         3,2  |
  3,3          |    3,2          |    3,3          |    3,2          |
          ]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="mif" title="Multiple Interfaces and other usecases">
      <t>The STUN attribute defined in this specification can be used by
      applications in the following scenarios:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>When an endpoint has multiple interfaces (for example 3G, 4G,
          WiFi, VPN, etc.), an ICE agent can choose the interfaces for media
          streams according to the path characteristics. After STUN responses
          to STUN checks are received, the ICE agent using regular nomination
          can sort the ICE candidate pairs according to the path
          characteristics discovered using STUN. The controlling agent can
          assign highest priority to candidate pair which best fulfills the
          desired path characteristics.</t>

          <t>[TODO: Add details of
          http://juberti.github.io/draughts/nombis/draft-uberti-mmusic-nombis.html
          that explains simplifying and improving the procedures for candidate
          nomination in ICE to make dynamic decisions.]</t>

          <t>When a host has multiple interfaces available an <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-avtcore-mprtp">MPRTP</xref> application can choose
          the interface for the primary subflow and interfaces for subsequent
          subflows according to the path characteristics discovered using
          STUN. For example, the scheduling algorithm described in <xref
          target="ACM-MPRTP"></xref> uses both path loss and latency for
          choosing the most suitable subset of paths.</t>

          <t>The STUN extension proposed in this specification can also be
          used to choose a TURN server that provides the best user experience
          (section 3.1 of <xref
          target="I-D.patil-tram-turn-serv-selection"></xref>).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>[Paragraphs in braces should be removed by the RFC Editor upon
      publication]</t>

      <t>[The PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute requires that IANA allocate a
      value in the "STUN attributes Registry" from the comprehension-optional
      range (0x8000-0xFFFF), to be replaced for TBD-CA throughout this
      document]</t>

      <t>This document defines the PATH-CHARACTERISTIC STUN attribute,
      described in <xref target="alg_over"></xref>. IANA has allocated the
      comprehension-optional codepoint TBD-CA for this attribute.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations discussed in <xref target="RFC5389"></xref>
      are to be taken into account. STUN requires the 96 bits transaction ID
      to be uniformly and randomly chosen from the interval 0 .. 2**96-1, and
      be cryptographically strong. This is good enough security against an
      off-path attacker. An on-path attacker can either inject a fake response
      or modify the values in PATH-CHARACTERISTIC attribute to mislead the
      client and server, this attack can be mitigated using STUN
      authentication. As PATH-CHARACTERISTIC is expected to be used between
      peers using ICE, and ICE uses STUN short-term credential mechanism the
      risk of on-path attack influencing the messages is minimal. However, an
      attacker could corrupt, remove, or delay an ICE request or response, in
      order to discourage that path from being used.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TODO</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5245"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"  ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.patil-tram-turn-serv-selection'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-avtcore-mprtp'?>

      <reference anchor="ACM-MPRTP">
        <front>
          <title>MPRTP: multipath considerations for real-time media</title>

          <author fullname="Varun Singh" initials="V." surname="Singh"></author>

          <author fullname="Saba Ahsan" initials="S." surname="Ahsan"></author>

          <author fullname="Joerg Ott" initials="J." surname="Ott"></author>

          <date year="2013" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="in Proc. of ACM Multimedia Systems," value="MMSys" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
