<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-wing-dnsop-dnsod-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DNS over DTLS (DNSoD)">DNS over DTLS (DNSoD)</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>

          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>California</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Prashanth Patil" initials="P." surname="Patil">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <street/>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>praspati@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <workgroup>DNSOP Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>DNS queries and responses are visible to network elements on
      the path between the DNS client and its server.  These queries
      and responses can contain privacy-sensitive information which is
      valuable to protect.  An active attacker can send bogus
      responses causing misdirection of the subsequent connection.</t>

      <t>To counter passive listening and active attacks, this
      document proposes the use of Datagram Transport Layer Security
      (DTLS) for DNS, to protect against passive listeners and certain
      active attacks.  As DNS needs to remain fast, this proposal also
      discusses mechanisms to reduce DTLS round trips and reduce DTLS 
      handshake size.  The proposed mechanism runs over the default
      DNS port and can also run over an alternate port.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>The Domain Name System is specified in
      <xref target="RFC1034"/> and <xref target="RFC1035"/>. DNS
      queries and responses are normally exchanged unencrypted and are
      thus vulnerable to eavesdropping.  Such
      eavesdropping can result in an undesired entity learning domains
      that a host wishes to access, thus resulting in privacy
      leakage. DNS privacy problem is further discussed in
      <xref target="I-D.bortzmeyer-dnsop-dns-privacy"/>.</t>

      <t>Active attackers have long been successful at injecting bogus
      responses, causing cache poisoning and causing misdirection of
      the subsequent connection (if attacking A or AAAA records).  A
      popular mitigation against that attack is to use ephemeral and
      random source ports for DNS queries.</t>

      <t>This document defines DNS-over-DTLS (DNSoD, pronounced
      "dee-enn-sod") which provies confidential DNS communication for
      stub resolvers, recursive resolvers, iterative resolvers and
      authoritative servers.</t>
</section>

<section title="Relationship to TCP Queries and to DNSSEC">
  <t>DNS queries can be sent over UDP or TCP.  This document scope is
only UDP.  DNS over TCP could be protected with TLS, such as described
by <xref target="I-D.hzhwm-start-tls-for-dns"/>.  Alternatively, a
shim protocol could be defined by DNSoD between DTLS and DNS, allowing
large responses to be sent over DTLS itself, see
<xref target="performance"/>.</t>

      <t>DNS Security Extensions
      (<xref target="RFC4033">DNSSEC</xref>) provides object integrity
      of DNS resource records, allowing end-users (or their resolver)
      to verify legitimacy of responses.  However, DNSSEC does not
      protect privacy of DNS requests or responses. DNSoD works in
      conjuction with DNSSEC, but DNSoD does not replace the need or
      value of DNSSEC.</t>
</section>

    <section anchor="term" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="problem_stmt" title="Incremental Deployment">
    <t>DNSoD can be deployed incrementally by the Internet Service
  Provider or as an Intenet service.</t>
    <t>If the ISP's DNS resolver supports DNSoD, then DNS queries are
    protected from passive listening and from many active attacks along
    that path.</t>

    <t>DNSoD can be offered as an Internet service, and a DNS resolver
    can be configured to point that that DNSoD server (rather than
    to the ISP-provided DNS server).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="demux" title="Demultiplexing, Polling, Port Usage, and Discovery">
     <t>[Note - This section requires further discussion]</t>

     <t>Many modern operating systems already detect if a web proxy is
     interfering with Internet communications, using proprietary
     mechanisms that are out of scope of this document.  After that
     mechanism has run (and detected Internet connectivity is
     working), the DNSoD procedure described in this document
     should commence.  This timing avoids delays in joining the
     network (and displaying an icon indicating successful Internet
     connection), at the risk that those initial DNS queries will be
     sent without protection afforded by DNSoD.  </t>

     <t>DNSoD can run over standard UDP port 53 as defined in
     <xref target="RFC1035"/>.  A DNS client or server that does not
     implement this specification will not respond to the incoming
     DTLS packets because they don't parse as DNS packets (the DNS
     Opcode would be 15, which is undefined).  A DNS client or server
     that does implement this specification can demultiplex DNS and
     DTLS packets by examining the third octet.  For TLS 1.2, which is
     what is defined by this specification, A DTLS packet will contain
     253 in the third octet, whereas a DNS packet will never contain
     253 in the third octet.</t>

<t>There has been some concern with sending DTLS-over-DNS traffic
over the same port as normal, un-encrypted DNS traffic.  The intent
of this section is to show that DNSoD could successfully
be sent over port 53.  Further analysis and testing on the Internet
may be valuable to determine if multiplexing on port 53, using
a separate port, or some fallback between a separate port and port
53 brings the most success.</t>



      <t>After performing the above steps, the host should determine
      if the DNS server supports DNSoD by sending a DTLS
      ClientHello message.  A DNS server that does not support
      DNSoD will not respond to ClientHello messages sent by
      the client, because they are not valid DNS requests
      (specifically, the DNS Opcode is invalid).  The client MUST use
      timer values defined in 4.2.4.1 of <xref target="RFC6347"/> for
      retransmission of ClientHello message and if no response is
      received from the DNS server.  After 15 seconds, it MUST cease
      attempts to re-transmit its ClientHello.  Thereafter, the client
      MAY repeat that procedure in the event the DNS server has been
      upgraded to support DNS over DTLS, but such probing SHOULD NOT
      be done more frequently than every 24 hours and MUST NOT be done
      more frequently than every 15 minutes.  This mechnism requires
      no additional signaling between the client and server. </t>
    </section>

<section anchor="performance" title="Performance Considerations">
<t>To reduce number of octets of the DTLS handshake, especially the
size of the certificate sent by the server (which can be several
kilobytes), we should examine viability of using plain public keys
<xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-oob-pubkey"/>.  Considering that to
authorize a certain DNS server the client already needs explicit
configuration of a whitelist of the DNS servers it trusts, maybe the
public key configuration problem is really no worse than the
configuration problem of those whitelisted certificates?</t>

<t>Multiple DNS queries can be sent over a single DNSoD security
association. The existing QueryID allows multiple requests and
responses to be interleaved in whatever order they can be fulfilled by
the DNS server.  This means DNSoD reduces the consumption of UDP port
numbers, and because DTLS protects the communication between the DNS
client and its server, the resolver SHOULD NOT use random ephemeral
source ports (Section 9.2 of <xref target="RFC5452"/>) because such
source port use would incur additional, unnecessary DTLS load on the
DNSoD server.</t>

<t>It is highly advantageous to avoid server-side DTLS state and
reduce the number of new DTLS security associations on the server
which can be done with <xref target="RFC5077"/>.  This also eliminates
a round-trip for subsequent DNSoD queries, because with
<xref target="RFC5077"/> the DTLS security association does not need
to be re-established.  The use of <xref target="RFC5077"/> also assists
with DNS anycast (see also <xref target="anycast"/>).  Note: with
the shim (described below) perhaps we could send the query and
the restore server-side state in the ClientHello packet.</t>

<t>Compared to normal DNS, DTLS adds at least 13 octets of header,
plus cipher and authentication overhead to every query and every
response.  This reduces the size of the DNS payload that can be
carried.  Certain DNS responses are large (e.g., many AAAA records,
TXT, SRV) and don't fit into a single UDP packet, causing a partial
response with the truncation (TC) bit set.  The client is then
expected to repeat the query over TCP, which causes additional name
resolution delay.  We have considered two ideas, one that reduces the
need to switch to TCP and another that eliminates the need to switch
to TCP:
<list style="symbols"><t>Path MTU can be determined
using <xref target="RFC4821">Packetization Layer Path MTU
Discovery</xref> using DTLS heartbeat.  <xref target="RFC4821"/> does
not rely on ICMP or ICMPv6, and would not affect DNS state or
responsiveness on the client or server.  However, it would be
additional chattiness.</t>
<t>To avoid IP fragmentation, DTLS handshake messages incorporate their
own fragmentat offset and fragment length.  We might utilize a similar
mechanism in a shim layer between DTLS and DNS, so that large DNS
messages could be carried without causing IP fragmentation.</t>
</list></t>

</section>


    <section anchor="in_band_signaling" title="In-Band Signaling">
      <t>Probing with DTLS ClientHello packets to determine if a DNS
server supports DNSoD is somewhat inefficient, as it requires multiple
probe packets to each DNS server.  It may well be preferable to have a
method of determining, within the DNS protocol itself, if a certain
DNS server supports DNSoD. Two approaches are discussed below, one
using DNS SRV query or <xref target="RFC4892">Name Server
Instance</xref> query, and another extending the EDNS0 OPT meta-RR
<xref target="I-D.hzhwm-start-tls-for-dns"/> to describe DNSoD
support.</t>

<t>To use <xref target="RFC4892">Name Server Instance</xref> query, we
would define a new CHAOS class resource record.  The name is not
significant, so let's pretend it would be called "DNSoD".  Note:
we might to indicate an alternate port, querying a CHAOS SRV
resource record is probably most ideal.</t>


      <t>To extend the EDNS0 OPT meta-RR defined in
<xref target="I-D.hzhwm-start-tls-for-dns"/>, we can add another bit
indicating support for DNSoD, denoted as "SO".  Clients and servers
indicate their support for, and desire to use, DNS over DTLS by
setting a bit in the Flags field of the EDNS0 <xref target="RFC6891"/>
OPT meta-RR. The "DTLS OK" (SO) bit is defined as the third bit of the
third and fourth bytes of the "extended RCODE and flags" portion of
the EDNS0 OPT meta-RR, immediately adjacent to the "TLS OK" (TO) bit
defined in <xref target="I-D.hzhwm-start-tls-for-dns"/>, as shown below:</t>

      <figure align="center">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
           +0 (MSB)                +1 (LSB)
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
0: |   EXTENDED-RCODE      |       VERSION         |
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
2: |DO|TO|SO|            Must be zero              |
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+]]></artwork>
      </figure>

</section>

<!--
      <section title="Use by DNS clients">
-->

<section title="Authenticating a DNS Server">
<t>As DTLS provides integrity protection, some protection from on-path
      attackers sending bogus responses is provided by simply using
      DTLS.  That is, a device on the path between a DNS client and
      its DNS server cannot simply inject a bogus DNS response, as
      could be done with normal DNS.  However, that protection is not
      terribly strong, because that attacker could intercept the DTLS
      handshake itself and pretend to be the actual DNS server.  To
      prevent that, we need to resolve two problems: identifying the
      trusted servers and determinnig an appropriate action when no
      trusted servers are available.</t>

      <t>The first problem, of identifying the legitimate server,
      requires extending the host configuration.  This is because DNS
      clients have their DNS servers configured by IP address (from
      DHCP or from a local configuration file such as
      /etc/resolv.conf), but certificates have a DNS name in the
      SubjectAltName field.  We can't change how certificates are
      issued, but we already have to modify the DNS client to support
      DNSoD.  With that in mind, the DNS client would have a
      list of SubjectAltNames it trusts, configured by the user.  That
      could be configured in the resolv.conf file itself, as shown below,
      or could be maintained in a separate file.</t>
     <figure align="center">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[nameserver 192.0.2.1    dns.example.net
nameserver 198.51.100.1 dns.example.com]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The second problem is determining an appropriate action when
     no trusted servers are available.  Although the DNS client could
     still use DNSoD with an un-trusted server which still
     provides protection from on-path passive listeners and from on-
     and off-path active attackers, this use does not protect from a
     malicious server returning bogus responses.  While DNSSEC can protect
     against bogus responses (lies), DNSSEC cannot protect against a 
     server that simply does not return certain answers.

	<list style="empty"><t>[[Editor's Note: Is there more we could
     do?  Trust certain responses (like for my enterprise VPN or other
     sites where I will be doing a TLS handshake)?  Keep in mind that
     with web portals at hotels/airports, we won't have access to a
     trusted DNS server on initial connect at all.]] </t></list></t>
</section>


<!--

dwing:  this section needs a re-write

        <section title="Sending Queries">
          <t>DNS clients MAY set the SO bit in queries sent using UDP
          transport to signal their general ability to support DNS over DTLS.
          [For discussion: is this a bad idea because ignorant middleboxes
          might drop the SO=1 UDP queries?]</t>

          <t>DNS clients MAY set the SO bit in the initial query sent to a
          server using UDP transport to signal their desire that the UDP
          connection be upgraded to DTLS.  DNS clients MUST NOT set the SO bit
          on subsequent queries when already using DNS over DTLS.</t>

          <t>Since the motivation for DNS over DTLS is to preserve
          privacy, DNS clients SHOULD use a query that reveals no
          private information in the initial SO=1 query to a
          server. To provide a standard "dummy" query, it is
          RECOMMENDED to do a CHAOS SRV resource record query
          <xref target="RFC4892"/>.</t>

          <t>After sending the initial SO=1 query using UDP transport, DNS
          clients MUST wait for the initial response before sending any
          subsequent queries over the same UDP connection.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Receiving Responses">
          <t>A DNS client that receives a response that matches its outstanding
          request with the Meta RR with the SO bit set SHOULD record
          the server's support for DNSoD and use that information as
          part of its server selection algorithm in the case where multiple
          servers are available to service a particular query. [For
          discussion: UDP is subject to spoofing and a client which depends on
          SO=1 in a UDP response may be tricked into never upgrading to
          DTLS.]</t>

          <t>A DNS client that receives a response to its initial query using
          UDP transport that has the SO bit set SHOULD immediately initiate a
          DTLS handshake using the procedure described in <xref
          target="RFC6347"/>.</t>

          <t>A DNS client that receives a response to its initial query using
          UDP transport that has the SO bit clear MUST not initiate a DTLS
          handshake and SHOULD utilize the existing UDP connection for
          subsequent queries. DNS clients SHOULD remember server IP addresses
          that don't support DNS over DTLS and SHOULD NOT request DNS over
          DTLS from them for reasonable period. (We suggest 1 hour, or when
          the client discovers a new resolver)</t>
        </section>

      </section>
-->



<!-- dwing: this section also needs a re-write.  What new thing are we
trying to explain?  We need more than just how to handle the Meta RR;
we need to describe how to demultiplex the arriving packet (DNS or
DTLS)

      <section title="Use by DNS Servers">
        <section title="Receiving a Query">

          <t>A DNS server receiving a query over TCP with the EDNS0
          OPT meta Resource Record with the SO bit set it MUST ignore that
          SO bit.  [Editor's Note:  is there interoperability harm if
          it responds properly to that query?].</t>

          <t>A DNS server receiving a query over an existing DTLS session MUST
          ignore the SO bit.</t>
why ignore?  what harm occurs?

          <t>A DNS server receiving an initial query over UDP that has the SO
          bit set MAY inform the client it is willing to establish a DTLS
          session, as described in the next section.</t>

          <t>A DNS server receiving subsequent queries over a DTLS session
          MUST ignore the SO bit.</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Sending Responses">
          <t>A DNS server sending a response over UDP SHOULD set the SO bit to
          indicate its general support for DNS over DTLS, as long as it is
          willing and able to support a DTLS connection with the particular
          client. A DNS server receiving an initial query over UDP that has
          the SO bit set MAY set the TO bit in its response. The server MUST
          then proceed with the DTLS handshake protocol. A DNS server
          receiving a "dummy" STARTDTLS/CH/TXT query over UDP MUST respond
          with RCODE=0 and a TXT RR in the Answer section. Contents of the TXT
          RR are strictly informative (for humans) and MUST NOT be interpreted
          by the client software. Recommended TXT RDATA values are "STARTDTLS"
          or "NO_DTLS".</t>
        </section>
      </section>
-->


    <section anchor="DTLS" title="Established sessions">
      <t>In DTLS, all data is protected using the same record encoding and
      mechanisms. When the mechanism described in this document is in effect,
      DNS messages are encrypted using the standard DTLS record encoding. When
      a user of DTLS wishes to send an DNS message, it delivers it to the DTLS
      implementation as an ordinary application data write (e.g.,
      SSL_write()). A single DTLS session can be used to receive multiple DNS
      requests and generate DNS multiple responses.</t>

      <figure title="Message Flow for Full Handshake Issuing New Session Ticket">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   Client                                          Server
   ------                                          ------

   ClientHello             -------->  
                         

                           <-------    HelloVerifyRequest  
                                         (contains cookie)    

   ClientHello             -------->     
   (contains cookie)                      
   (empty SessionTicket extension)
                                              ServerHello  
                                  (empty SessionTicket extension)  
                                             Certificate*    
                                       ServerKeyExchange*      
                                      CertificateRequest*     
                           <--------      ServerHelloDone    

   Certificate*                                             
   ClientKeyExchange                                          
   CertificateVerify*                                          
   [ChangeCipherSpec]                                         
   Finished                -------->                         
                                         NewSessionTicket
                                       [ChangeCipherSpec]    
                           <--------             Finished    

  
   DNS Request             --------->

                           <---------  DNS Response

]]></artwork>
      </figure>


    </section>

<section anchor="anycast" title="Interaction with DNS Anycast">
<t>DNS servers often use anycast, either within a single datacenter or
in geographic regions.  Normal DNS is completely stateless so if two
queries happen to arrive at two different anycasted DNS servers, normal
DNS works fine.  However, because DNSoD also carries a security
association, the queries have to be sent to a server that already has
(or can acquire) the necessary security association.  If the DNSoD
client sends <xref target="RFC5077"/> to a server that had never 
seen a DNSoD request from this client, and that server is part of
an DNS anycast network, <xref target="RFC5077"/> can instantiate
the necessary DTLS state in the DNSoD server.</t>

<t>However, because several DNS queries can be sent within one DTLS
session (and thus it doesn't always start witha DTLS ClientHello), a
load balancer is necessary ensure the same source IP address and UDP
port is routed to the same DNSoD server that has the necessary security
association.  This only works within a datacenter, of course.  When
anycast DNS servers are deployed across a geographic region, route
flapping can cause subequent DNSoD traffic to arrive at an anycasted
DNS server that has no security association.  When this occurs, to
avoid the DNSoD client from timing out, the DNSoD server MUST 
respond with a DTLS 'alert' error.</t>
</section>


    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document defines a new bit ("SO") in the Flags field of the
      EDNS0 OPT meta-RR. At the time of approval of this draft in the
      standards track, as per the IANA Considerations of <xref
      target="RFC6891"/>, IANA is requested to reserve the third leftmost bit
      of the flags as the SO bit, immediately adjacent to the DNSSEC SO bit,
      as shown in <xref target="in_band_signaling"/>.</t>

<t>If demultiplexing DTLS and DNS (using the third octet,
<xref target="demux"/>) is useful, we should reserve DNS Opcode 15 to
ensure DNS always has a 0 bit where DTLS always has a 1 bit.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Once a DNSoD client has established a security association
     with a particular DNS server, and outstanding normal DNS queries
     with that server (if any) have been received, the DNSoD client
     MUST ignore any subsequent normal DNS responses from that server,
     as all subsequent responses should be inside DNSoD.  This
     behavior mitigates all (?) attacks described
     in <xref target="RFC5452">Measures for Making DNS More Resilient
     against Forged Answers</xref>.</t>

     <t>Security considerations discussed
      in <xref target="RFC6347">DTLS</xref> also apply to this
      document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The EDNS0 OPT meta-RR described in <xref target="in_band_signaling"/>
      are an extension of the technique described in
      <xref target="I-D.hzhwm-start-tls-for-dns">DNS-over-TLS</xref>.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Phil Hedrick for his review comments on TCP.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1034"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1035"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4033"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5077"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6347"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6891"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5452"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.bortzmeyer-dnsop-dns-privacy'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.hzhwm-start-tls-for-dns'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-tls-oob-pubkey'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4892"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4821"?>


      <reference anchor="IANA-domain" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/special-use-domain-names/special-use-domain-names.xhtml">
	<front>
          <title>Special-Use Domain Names</title>

          <author>
	    <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2013"/>
	  </front>
      </reference>



    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
