<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5245 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5245.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5389 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5389.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4594 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4594.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>
<?rfc tocindent='yes' ?>
adsad

<?rfc needLines="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-martinsen-mmusic-malice-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MALICE">Meta-data Attribute signaLling with ICE</title>

    
    <author fullname="Paal-Erik Martinsen" initials="P.E" surname="Martinsen">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Philip Pedersens vei 20</street>

          <city>Lysaker</city>

          <region>Akershus</region>

          <code>1366</code>

          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>

        <email>palmarti@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Anca Zamfir" initials="A." surname="Zamfir">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>EPFL, Quartier de l'Innovation</street>

          <city>Ecublens</city>

          <region>Vaud</region>

          <code>1015</code>

          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ancaz@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>
    <workgroup>MMUSIC</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>It can be useful for applications to provide flow metadata information
      to on-path devices to influence flow treatment in the
      network. Provided that the network is able to provide
      useful feedback, this can also influence path
      selection if an application have multiple flow paths to choose from.</t>
      
      <t>This draft describes how this can be achieved by adding
      metadata to the STUN packets sent during the ICE connectivity
      checks or a slightly modified version of the keep-alive
      mechanism. Devices on the
      media path can use the metadata information to prioritize the flow,
      perform traffic engineering, or provide network analytics and
      notifications as requested by the endpoints. On-path devices can append
      or modify the existing metadata information in the STUN/ICE
      messages to enable feedback to other on-path devices or the
      applications in both ends of the media session.</t>

      <t>This document describes a framework mechanism for how such metadata
      can be transported by STUN when ICE is in use and it covers the endpoint
      and on path device processing. The functionality described here is
      referred to as MALICE.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Problem Statement">
      <t>In the context of Content, Mobile, Fixed Service, Service
      Providers, Enterprise and Private networks have a need to
      prioritize packet flows end-to-end. These flows
      are often dynamic, time-bound, encrypted, peer-to-peer, possibly
      asymmetric, and might have different priorities depending on network
      conditions, direction, time of the day, dynamic user preferences and
      other factors. These factors may be time variant, and thus need to be
      signalled. Moreover, in many cases of peer-to-peer communication, flow
      information is known only to the endpoint. These considerations, coupled
      with the trend to use encryption for browser-to-browser communication
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch"/>, imply that access lists,
      deep packet inspection and other static prioritization methods cannot be
      employed successfully to prioritize packet flows. It can also be useful
      for the endpoints to provide flow metadata and receive network feedback
      in order select an optimal media communication path. This specification
      describes how these problems can be solved at different points in the
      network by using either STUN <xref target="RFC5389"/> packets
      sent during ICE's <xref target="RFC5245"/> connectivity check
      phase during establishment of a  media session, or as part a
      slightly modified keep-alive mechanism
      after the session is established. Devices on the media path can use the
      metadata information to prioritize the flow, perform traffic
      engineering, or provide network analytics and notifications as requested
      by the endpoints. On-path devices can append or modify the existing
      metadata information in the STUN/ICE messages. The ICE agents may use
      this information to learn about the status of their requests at on-path
      devices.</t>

      <t>This document describes a framework mechanism for how such metadata
      can be transported by STUN when ICE is in use with UDP based media and
      it covers the endpoint and middlebox processing. The functionality
      described here is referred to as MALICE.</t>
    </section>

   
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4732"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6398"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5245"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informational References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch' ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.muthu-behave-consent-freshness' ?>
    </references>

    <!--
 -->

    <!--
      -->
  </back>
</rfc>

