<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5245 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5245.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5389 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5389.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4594 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4594.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>
<?rfc tocindent='yes' ?>

<?rfc needLines="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-martinsen-aeon-malice-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MALICE">Meta-data Attribute signaLling with ICE</title>

    
    <author fullname="Paal-Erik Martinsen" initials="P.E" surname="Martinsen">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Philip Pedersens vei 20</street>
          <city>Lysaker</city>
          <region>Akershus</region>
          <code>1366</code>
          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>
        <email>palmarti@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <workgroup>AEON</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        It can be useful for applications to provide flow metadata
        information to on-path devices to influence flow treatment in
        the network.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        This draft describes how this can be achieved by adding
        metadata to the STUN packets sent during the ICE connectivity
        checks or keep-alive messages. Devices on the media path can
        use the metadata information to prioritize the flow, perform
        traffic engineering, or provide network analytics.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document describes a mechanism for how such metadata can
        be transported by STUN when ICE is in use. The functionality
        described here is referred to as MALICE.
      </t>  
    </abstract>
    
    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        In the context of Content, Mobile, Fixed Service, Service
        Providers, Enterprise and Private networks have a need to
        prioritize packet flows end-to-end. These flows are often
        dynamic, time-bound, encrypted, peer-to-peer, possibly
        asymmetric, and might have different priorities depending on
        network conditions, direction, time of the day, dynamic user
        preferences and other factors. These factors may be time
        variant, and thus need to be signalled. Moreover, in many
        cases of peer-to-peer communication, flow information is known
        only to the endpoint. These considerations, coupled with the
        trend to use encryption for browser-to-browser communication
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch"/>, imply that
        access lists, deep packet inspection and other static
        prioritization methods cannot be employed successfully to
        prioritize packet flows. This specification describes how
        these problems can be solved by using either STUN
        <xref target="RFC5389"/> packets sent during ICE's
        <xref target="RFC5245"/> connectivity check phase during
        establishment of a media session, or keep-alive mechanism
        after the session is established. Devices on the media path
        can use the metadata information to prioritize the flow,
        perform traffic engineering, or provide network analytics.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document describes a mechanism for how such metadata can
        be sent by STUN when ICE is in use with UDP based media. The
        functionality described here is referred to as MALICE. Due to
        the security implications described in (Martins draft) where
        large STUN packet are used amplify the attack, an decision
        consideration in MALICE is to keep the message size small.
      </t>

      <t>
        The META-DATA sent should be treated as informational by the
        network. No mechanisms for sending feedback from the network
        to the application are described in this document. 
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Sending Meta-data">
      <t>
        An application using ICE to negotiate the end to end media-path
        can add meta when sending the necessary STUN probing or
        keep-alive messages. Several Meta-data attributes can be added
        to a STUN message. This is especially useful in multiplexing
        scenarios such as BUNDLE where several media streams are sent
        on the same 5-tuple.
      </t>

      <section title="Adding Meta-data to connectivity cheks">
        <t>
          An ICE connectivity check is performed by sending a STUN
          Binding request. Prior to sending the agent can add one or
          more meta-data attributes to the Binding Request. Values in
          the Meta-data attribute are usually default values configured
          by the agent.
        </t>
        <t>
          An agent receiving STUN Binding requests with Meta-Data
          attributes can successfully use that information to set up
          for example audio or video decoders. 
        </t>
        <t>
          Meta-data can also be added to the STUN Binding
          Responses. This will let the remote side know that the
          Meta-data was transported end-to-end on the path. Meta data
          SHOULD not be added to a response message unless Meta-data
          attributes was added to the corresponding Binding Request.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Adding Meta-data to keepalive messages">
        <t>
          An ICE connectivity check is performed by sending a STUN
          Binding indication. Prior to sending the agent can add one or
          more meta-data attributes to the Binding Indication. Values in
          the Meta-data attribute should reflect what is send in the
          stream at this point in time. 
        </t>
        <t>
          Problem with concent freshness if not based on STUN.
      </t>  
      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section title="New STUN attribute">
      <t>
        This STUN extension defines the following new attribute:
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
      0xXXXX: META-DATA  
           ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        This attribute have a length that are multiples of 4 (96) so
        no padding is necessary.
      </t>
      
      <figure anchor="META-data_attr" title="META-DATA Attribute">
            <artwork align="right"><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     META-DATA TYPE             |  Bandwith (kbps)             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                              Value (64 bits)                  |    
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
      <t>
        META-DATA TYPE a a 16 bit value defined in section ??
        describing the flow. The next 16 bits MUST be a number
        describing the approximate bandwidth usage in kbps. If this is
        unknown the value 0x0 is used. The rest of
        the 64 bits of the attribute is reserved for further
        description of the specific META-DATA type. This value field is thus
        dependant on the type field and entities not understanding the
        specific META-DATA type should ignore this when parsing.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="META-DATA types">
      
      <figure anchor="META-data_types" title="META-DATA Types">
            <artwork align="right"><![CDATA[
     0x0001 Generic 
     0x0002 Audio
     0x0003 Video
     0x0004 Application Data
      ]]></artwork>
          </figure>


      <section title="Generic">
        
        <figure anchor="META-data_genericr" title="META-DATA
                                                   Type Generic">
          <artwork align="right"><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            0x0001              |      Bandwidth (kbps)        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| max retransmit|  retransmits   |           0xFF               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
|                              0xFFFF                           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

      ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          
          <t hangText="max retransmits:"> Maximal number of retransmits
            a client will do before giving up. For example a normal
            STUN transactions have 10 retransmits before it is
            considered as failed. RTP will typically have 0 retransmits.
          </t>

          <t hangText="retransmits:"> Current number of retransmits
          for non reliable packets in this stream. If this number is
          close to the mac retransmits it might be nice of the network
          element to concider not to drop the next packets coming.
          </t>

        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Audio">
      <figure anchor="META-data_audio" title="META-DATA
                                              Type Audio">
        <artwork align="right"><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            0x0002             |       Bandwidth (kbps)        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Sample Rate (Hz)           |          0xFF                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
|                              0xFFFF                           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

      ]]></artwork>
      </figure>        
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          
          <t hangText="Sample Rate:"> The current sample rate the
          audio codec used in this stream is sampled with.
          </t>
          
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Video">
        <figure anchor="META-data_video" title="META-DATA
                                                Type Video">
          <artwork align="right"><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            0x0003              |      Bandwidth (kbps)        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Vertical Resolution       |     Horizontal Resolution    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|             FPS                |          Jitter (ms)         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

      ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            
            <t hangText="Bandwidth:"> Bandwidth usage with video
            encoders are elastic. This value should indicate what max
            bandwidth value the encoder are set up to use. Dependant on
            movement in the picture and other video specific parameters
            the actual bandwidth usage might be lower than
            indicated. Note that this value can change over time as
            rate adaption algorithms in the encoder might change this
            value.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Vertical Resolution:"> Current vertical
            resolution used in the video encoded in the stream. Note
            that this value might change over time as the encoder might
            change this dependant on many different parameters. (In
            some instances a encoder can decide that changing from
            1080p30 to 720p60 will give the end user a better user
            experience)
            </t>
            
            <t hangText="Horizontal Resolution:"> Current horizontal
            resolution.
            </t>

            <t hangText="FPS:"> How many frames per seconds the video
            in the stream is encoded with.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>  
        
      </section>
      
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4732"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6398"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5245"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informational References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch' ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.muthu-behave-consent-freshness' ?>
    </references>

    <!--
 -->

    <!--
      -->
  </back>
</rfc>

