<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629xslt/rfc2629.dtd" [
      <!ENTITY rfc3667 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3667.xml'>
    ]>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc tocdepth='4'?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<!--rfc category="info" ipr="full3978"-->
<rfc category="std" ipr='trust200902'>
	<front>
		<title abbrev="DTLS-SRTP handling in SIP B2BUA">DTLS-SRTP handling in Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Back-to-Back User Agents (B2BUAs) </title>
		  <author initials="Parthasarathi" surname="Ravindran" fullname="Parthasarathi Ravindran">
			<organization>Nokia Solutions and Networks</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street> Manyata Embassy Business park </street>
					<city>Bangalore</city>
                           <code>560045</code>
					<region>Karnataka</region>
					<country>India</country>
				</postal>
				<email>partha@parthasarathi.co.in</email>
			</address>
		</author>
    <author fullname="Ram Mohan Ravindranath" initials="R"
            surname="Ravindranath">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park</street>

          <street>Sarjapur-Marathahalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rmohanr@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>

          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
		<date year="2014" />
		<area>Transport</area>
		<workgroup>STRAW</workgroup>
		<abstract>
		   <t>
		    SIP Back-to-Back User Agents (B2BUAs) are often envisaged to also be on the media path, rather than just intercepting signaling.  This document describes the behavior B2BUAs should follow when acting on the media plane that use Secure Real-time Transport Protocol (SRTP) security context setup with Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) protocol.
          </t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>

 <section title="Introduction">
<t>
	<xref target="RFC5763"/> describes how Session Initiation Protocol
   (SIP) can be used to establish a Secure Real-time Transport Protocol (SRTP)
   security context with Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS)
   protocol.  It describes a mechanism of transporting a certificate fingerprint in 
   Session Description Protocol (SDP), which identifies the certificate that will be presented during the DTLS handshake. DTLS-SRTP is defined for point-to-point media sessions, in which there are exactly two participants.  Each DTLS-SRTP session contains
   a single DTLS association, and either two SRTP contexts (if media traffic is flowing in both directions on the same host/port quartet) or one SRTP context (if media traffic is only flowing in one direction).  </t>
   <t>
   In may SIP deployments, SIP  entities exist in the SIP signaling path between the originating and final terminating endpoints. These SIP entities as described in  <xref target="RFC7092"/> modify SIP and SDP bodies and also are likely to be on the media path. Such Entities when present in the signaling/media path are likely to do several things. For example some B2BUAs modify parts of SDP (like IP address, port) and subsequently modify the RTP headers as well. There are other types of B2BUAs that would completely modify the RTP packet including the payload(like transcoder). In all these cases a DTLS association would break unless the B2BUA participates in the DTLS setup and ensures the context are setup properly. It is envisioned that B2BUA that are in media path MUST support DTLS stack and SRTP extensions needed for DTLS as described in <xref target="RFC5763"/> so that it can function as DTLS-SRTP proxy.
			</t>
			<t>
			<xref target="RFC7092"/> describes three different categories of such B2BUAs, according to the level of activities performed on the media plane:</t>
			<t><list style="hanging">
			 <t> A B2BUA that act as a simple media relay effectively unaware of anything that is transported and only modifies the UDP/IP header of the packets.</t>
			 <t> A B2BUA that performs a media-aware role. It inspects and potentially modifies RTP or RTCP headers, but it does not modify the payload of RTP/RTCP. </t>
			 <t> A B2BUA that performs a media-termination role and operates at the media payload layer, such as RTP/RTCP payload (For example Transcoder). </t>
			</list></t>
   
<t>
The following sections will describe the behaviour B2BUAs should follow in order to avoid  any impact on end-to-end DTLS-SRTP streams.</t>
</section>

<section title="Terminology" anchor="sec-term">
	<t>
		The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
		"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
		document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
				
	Readers of this document are expected to be aware of different B2BUA's defined in <xref target="RFC7092"/>.
	</t>
</section>
		
 <section title="Media plane B2BUAs">

   <section title="Media relay">
   <t>
    A media relay as identified in section 3.2.1 of <xref target="RFC7092"/> basically just forwards, from an application level point of view, all packets it receives on a negotiated UDP connection, without either inspecting or modifying them. They just forward the UDP payload as is by changing only the UDP/IP header.
   </t>
   <t> A media relay B2BUA MUST forward the certificate fingerprint it receives in SDP from the originating endpoint as is to the remote side and vice-versa. Below example shows a sample flow of Early Offer SIP SIP call with both endpoints doing DTLS-SRTP with a media relay B2BUA that changes the UDP/IP address/port.</t>
   
   <t><figure anchor="Figure1" title="Early Offer Media Relay B2BUA">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
 +-------+              +-----------------+        +-----------+         
 |  Alice|              | MediaRelay B2BUA|        |      Bob  |
 +-------+              +-----------------+        +-----------+
     |(1) INVITE               |  (3)INVITE                |
     |   a=setup:actpass       |   a=setup:actpass         |
     |   a=fingerprint1        |   a= fingerprint1         | 
     |   (alice's IP/port)     |   (B2BUA's IP, port)      |                        
     |------------------------>|  ------------------------>|
     |                         |                           |
     |    (2)  100 trying      |                           |
     | <-----------------------|                           |
     |                         | (4) 100 trying            |
     |                         | <-------------------------|
     |                         |                           |
     |                         |  (5)200 OK                |
     |                         |   a=setup:active          |
     |                         |    a=fingerprint2         |
     |                         |  (Bob's IP, port)         |
     |                         | <-------------------------|
     |    (6) 200 OK           |                           |
     |    a=setup:active       |                           |
     |    a=fingerprint2       |                           |
     |    B2BUA's address,port |                           |
     |               (7, 8)ClientHello + use_srtp          |
     |<------------------------|<--------------------------|
     |                         |                           |
     |                         |                           |
     |           (9,10)ServerHello + use_srtp              |
     |------------------------>|-------------------------->|
     |                 (11)    |                           |
     |  [Certificate exchange between Alice and Bob over   | 
     |   DTLS ]                |                           |  
     |                         |                           |
     |         (12)            |                           |
     |<---------SRTP/SRTCP---->|<----SRTP/SRTCP----------->|
     |   [B2BUA just changes UDP/IP header]                |   
      
     
     
     For the sake of brevity the entire fingerprint attribute is not shown.
          ]]></artwork></figure></t>
          
    <t> For each RTP or RTCP flow the peers do a DTLS handshake on the same source and destination port pair to establish a DTLS association. In this case Bob After he receives an INVITE triggers a DTLS connection. Note the DTLS handshake as well as the response to INVITE may happen in parallel and so the B2BUA SHOULD be prepared to receive media on the ports it advertised to Bob in the OFFER. Since a media relay B2BUA does not differentiate between a DTLS or RTP or any packet sent it just changes the UDP/IP addresses and forwards the packet on either leg.</t>
    
   </section>
   
   <section title="Media-aware relay or Media terminator">
   <t>A Media-aware relay, unlike the the Media Relay addressed in the
   previous section, is actually aware of the media traffic it is
   handling.  As such, it is able to inspect SRTP and SRTCP packets
   flowing by, and may even be able to modify the headers in any of them
   before forwarding them.  A B2BUA implementing this role would not,
   though, inspect the payloads as well, which would be opaque to
   them. </t>
   <t> A media terminator B2BUA in addition to modifying the header can modify parts of the payload. For example a Transcoder is a type of Media terminator that modifies the payload before it forwards the packet. It is envisioned that  these B2BUA's SHOULD have the capability the distinguish DTLS or SRTP or SRTCP or other packets (like STUN) received on the same udp port by using the algorithm mentioned in section 5.1.2 of <xref target="RFC5764"/> and takes care of handling them separately.</t>
   <t>Below example shows how a DTLS-SRTP session is setup for these B2BUA</t>
   
   <t><figure anchor="Figure2" title="Early Offer Media aware B2BUA">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
 +-------+              +-----------------+        +-----------+         
 |  Alice|              | MediaAware B2BUA|        |      Bob  |
 +-------+              +-----------------+        +-----------+
     |(1) INVITE               |  (3)INVITE                |
     |   a=setup:actpass       |   a=setup:actpass         |
     |   a=fingerprint1        |   a= fingerprint2         | 
     |   (alice's IP/port)     |   (B2BUA's IP, port)      |                        
     |------------------------>|  ------------------------>|
     |                         |                           |
     |    (2)  100 trying      |                           |
     | <-----------------------|                           |
     |                         | (4) 100 trying            |
     |                         | <-------------------------|
     |                         |                           |
     |                         |  (5)200 OK                |
     |                         |   a=setup:active          |
     |                         |    a=fingerprint3         |
     |                         |  (Bob's IP, port)         |
     |                         | <-------------------------|
     |                         |(6)ClientHello + use_srtp  |
     |                         |<--------------------------|
     |    (7) 200 OK           |                           |
     |    a=setup:active       | ServerHello + use_srtp (8)|
     |    a=fingerprint4       | ------------------------->|
     |    B2BUA's address,port |             (9,10)        |
     | <-----------------------|   [Cert Exchange between] |
     |  (11)ClientHello+       |      Bob and B2BUA over   |
     |     use_srtp            |              DTLS         |
     |<------------------------|                           |
     |  (12)ServerHello+       |                           |
     |   use_srtp              |                           |
     |------------------------>|                           |
     |                 (13,14  |                           |
     |  [Cert exchange between |                           |
     |   Alice and B2BUA       |                           |
     |   DTLS ]                |                           |
     |                         |                           |
     |         (15)            |          (16)             |
     |<---------SRTP/SRTCP---->|<----SRTP/SRTCP----------->|
     |   [B2BUA modifes SRTP/SRTCP header and/or payload]  |   
      
     
     
     For the sake of brevity the entire fingerprint attribute is not shown.
     Also the same flow would be applicable for Delayed Offer calls. 
          ]]></artwork></figure></t>
          
    <t>NOTE: Steps 5,6 may be parallel and so the B2BUA MAY receive ClientHello before it sees a 200OK. Steps 7,8 can happen in any order. Also steps 9,10, 11 may be parallel. B2BUA should be prepared to handle these responses on each leg independently.</t>
    
    <t>A media terminator B2BUA MUST change the certificate fingerprint from both the endpoints so that it can signal its own certificate fingerprint in the SDP. This way B2BUA can act as DTLS-SRTP proxy and modify the payload.</t>
    
   </section>
   
 </section>
		
		
           
<section title="DTLS-SRTP handling in B2BUA with signaling forking">
 <t> B2BUA's may receive multiple answers for an outbound INVITE due to downstream proxy forking the INVITE to multiple targets. It is possible that each of these responses have different certificate fingerprints. The B2BUA SHOULD take care of setting separate DTLS-SRTP associations with each of the forked targets.</t>
 </section>

   <section title="Security Considerations">
       <t> Security considerations in <xref target="RFC5763"/> should be taken into account.  </t>
			
 </section>

<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="sec.iana-considerations">
	<t>
      This document makes no request of IANA.
    </t>
</section>
	
<section title="Acknowledgement">
			
</section>

</middle>
	<back>
 		<references title="Normative References">
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5764"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5763"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7092"?>
            </references>
	</back>
</rfc>
