<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<!--rfc category="info" ipr="full3978"-->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ram-straw-b2bua-stun-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="STUN handling in SIP B2BUA">STUN message handling
    in Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Back-to-Back User Agents
    (B2BUAs)</title>

   <author fullname="Ram Mohan Ravindranath" initials="R."
            surname="Ravindranath">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park</street>

          <street>Sarjapur-Marathahalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rmohanr@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T."
            surname="Reddy">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>

          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Gonzalo Salgueiro" initials="G."
            surname="Salgueiro">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>7200-12 Kit Creek Road</street>

          <city>Research Triangle Park</city>

          <region>NC</region>

          <code>27709</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>gsalguei@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2014"/>

    <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructre (RAI)</area>

    <workgroup>STRAW</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>SIP Back-to-Back User Agents (B2BUAs) are often envisaged to be on the media path, rather than just intercepting signaling.  This means that B2BUAs often act on the media path leading to separate media legs that the B2BUA correlates and bridges together. When acting on the media path, the B2BUAs are likely to receive packets like STUN for ICE apart from the media packets. It is critical that the B2BUAs handle these STUN messages properly.</t>
<t>This document defines the proper behavior B2BUAs should follow when
   STUN messages are sent on the media path.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
    <t>Protocols using offer/answer like the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)
   <xref target="RFC3261"/> are difficult to operate through Network
   Address Translators (NAT) because they carry IP addresses within their 
   messages.  To remedy this, an extension to SDP <xref target="RFC4566"/>, 
   called Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE) has been defined <xref
    target="RFC5245"/>.  ICE defines procedures by which agents gather a 
    multiplicity of addresses, include all of them in an SDP offer or answer, 
    and then use peer-to-peer connectivity checks using Session Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN) <xref target="RFC5389"/>  to determine a valid candidate pair for each media stream.</t>

      <t>In many SIP deployments, SIP entities exist in the SIP
      signaling path between the originating and final terminating
      endpoints. These SIP entities, as described in <xref
      target="RFC7092"/>, modify SIP headers, SDP bodies and also are
      likely to be on the media path. Such entities, when present in
      the media path, are likely to do several things. For
      example, some B2BUAs modify parts of the SDP body (like IP
      address, port) and subsequently modify the transport headers as well.
      There are other types of B2BUAs that completely modify the transport payload.  (e.g., a media transcoder).</t>
      <t> Section 18.6 of ICE <xref target="RFC5245"/> explains about two different behaviors when B2BUAs are present.  Some B2BUAs are likely to remove all the SDP ICE attributes before sending the SDP across to the other side.  Consequently, the call will appear to both endpoints as if the other side doesn't support ICE.  There are other types of B2BUAs that passes the ICE attributes without modification, yet modifies the default destination for media (contained in the m and c lines and rtcp attribute), this will be detected as an ICE mismatch, and ICE processing is aborted for the call. This behavior of disabling ICE is not always desirable especially when one of the endpoints is behind a NAT.</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC7092"/> describes three different categories
      of such B2BUAs, according to the level of activities performed
      on the media plane:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t>A B2BUA that acts as a simple media relay effectively
          unaware of anything that is transported and only modifies
          the transport header (could be UDP/IP) of the media packets.</t>

          <t>A B2BUA that performs a media-aware role. It inspects and
          potentially modifies RTP or RTP Control Protocol (RTCP)
          headers; but it does not modify the payload of RTP/RTCP.</t>

          <t>A B2BUA that performs a media-termination role and
          operates at the media payload layer, such as RTP/RTCP
          payload (e.g., a transcoder).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>When such a B2BUA operating on a media plane is involved a call between 
      two endpoints that performs ICE, then it SHOULD follow the behavior mentioned in this specification.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-term" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
      in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

      <t>The following generalized terms are defined in <xref
      target="RFC3261"/>, Section 6.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t>B2BUA: A SIP Back-to-Back User Agent, which is the
          logical combination of a User Agent Server (UAS) and User
          Agent Client (UAC).</t>

          <t>UAS: A SIP User Agent Server.</t>

          <t>UAC: A SIP User Agent Client.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>All of the pertinent B2BUA terminology and taxonomy used in
      this document is based on <xref target="RFC7092"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Media Plane B2BUAs">
      <section title="Media Relay or Media aware or Media Termination">
        
        <t>When one or both the endpoints are behind NAT, and there is a B2BUA
       between the endpoints, it is desirable to have the B2BUA support ICE or
        at the minimum support ICE LITE functionality as described in <xref 
        target="RFC5245"/>. Such B2BUAs MUST implement ICE and STUN and 
        handle STUN messages sent by the endpoints on the media path. B2BUAs 
        MUST use the mechanism described in section 5.1.2 of <xref 
        target="RFC5764"/> to demultiplex STUN packets that arrive on the 
        RTP/RTCP port.</t>
        
        <t>A B2BUA operating on a media plane MUST follow the below steps when 
        it receives a SDP with ICE semantics. </t>

         <t><list style="hanging">
          <t>When a B2BUA receives a SDP OFFER with ICE semantics it MUST respond with a SDP ANSWER having ICE candidates. A B2BUA MAY be in ICE lite mode as described in section 2.7 of <xref target="RFC5245"/> in which case it MUST send a=ice-lite and MUST include host candidates for each component of each media stream.</t>
          <t>If the B2BUA supports full ICE, then it MAY include candidates of different types for each component of each media stream in the SDP offer/answer.</t>
          <t> A B2BUA when it sends out  SDP with OFFER, it MUST advertise support for ICE and MAY include candidates of different types for each component of each media stream.</t>
          <t>The B2BUA MUST generate new username, password values for ice- ufrag and ice-pwd attributes when it sends out the SDP and MUST NOT propagate the ufrag/password values it received in the incoming SDP. This ensures that the short-term credentials used for both the legs are different. B2BUA terminates the STUN message on each leg, generates new STUN message using new cryptographically-random <xref target="RFC4086"/> STUN transaction ID and computes the message integrity for STUN messages using the new credentials.</t>
          <t>The B2BUA MUST generate and/or respond to ICE connectivity checks after offer/answer is completed.</t>
          </list></t>
          
        <t><figure anchor="Figure1"
            title="INVITE with SDP having ICE and with a Media Plane B2BUA">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 +-------+            +------------------+              +-----+         
 | Alice |            | Mediaplane B2BUA |              | Bob |
 +-------+            +------------------+              +-----+
     |(1) INVITE               |  (3)INVITE                |
     |   a=ice-ufrag1          |    a=ice-ufrag2           |
     |   a=ice-pwd1            |     a=ice-pwd2            |
     |   (alice's IP/port)     |   (B2BUA's IP, port)      |   
     |(Alice's candidate list )|   (B2BUA's candidate list)|                        
     |------------------------>|-------------------------->|
     |                         |                           |
     |    (2)  100 trying      |                           |
     |<------------------------|                           |
     |                         | (4) 100 trying            |
     |                         |<--------------------------|
     |                         |  (5)200 OK                |
     |                         |   a=ice-ufrag3            |
     |                         |    a=ice-pwd3             |
     |                         |   a=setup:active          |
     |                         |    a=fingerprint2         |
     |                         |  (Bob's IP, port)         |
     |                         | (Bob's candidate list)    |
     |                         | <-------------------------|
     |    (6) 200 OK           |                           |
     |    a=ice-ufrag4         | ----------ACK------------>|
     |    a=ice-pwd4           |           (7)             |
     |    a=setup:active       |                           |
     |    a=fingerprint2       |                           |
     |    B2BUA's address,port |                           |
     | (B2BUA's cand list1)    |                           |
     |<------------------------|                           |
     | -------ACK------------->|                           |
     |              (8)        |                           |
     |                         |                           |
     |<----ICE Connectivity 1->|                           |
     |      checks+conclusion  |<-----ICE Connectivity 2-->|
     |         (9)             |        checks +conclusion |
     |                         |         (10)              |
     |<-------Media packets -->|<----Media packets-------->|
     |      (13)               |         (14)              |  
     |                         |                           |
     |<---ICE keepalives 1---->|                           |
     |        (15)             |<----ICE keep alives 2---->|            
                                      (16)
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Above figure shows a sample call flow with two endpoints Alice and Bob doing ICE and a B2BUA handing STUN messages from both the endpoints. For the sake of brevity the entire ICE SDP attributes are not shown. Also the STUN messages exchanged as part of ICE connectivity checks are not shown. Key steps to note from the call flow are:</t>
       <t><list style="numbers">
       <t>Alice sends an INVITE with SDP offer having ICE candidates.</t>
       <t> B2BUA modifies the received SDP from Alice by removing the received candidates, gathers its own candidates, updates ice-ufrag, ice-password attributes with new username, password values and forwards the INVITE (3) to Bob.</t>
       <t> Bobs responds(5) to the INVITE with his own list of candidates. </t>
       <t> B2BUA responds to the INVITE from Alice with SDP having B2BUA's candidate list. B2BUA would also convey ice-ufrag, ice-password attributes with  new username, password values in the 200 OK response(6). </t>
       <t>ICE Connectivity checks happen between Alice and B2BUA in step 9. 
       Depending on whether the B2BUA supports ICE or ICE lite it will follow 
       the appropriate procedures mentioned in <xref target="RFC5245"/>. The 
       B2BUA MUST process the STUN request sent by Alice and respond to the same 
       without forwarding it to the other side (Bob).</t>
       <t>ICE Connectivity checks also happen between Bob and B2BUA in step 10. Step 9, 10 happens in parallel and STUN messages on each side MUST NOT be forwarded to the other side by the B2BUA. </t>
       <t> Once ICE is completed on each side, there MAY be a updated SIP
       offer/answer (steps 11 to 14).</t>
       <t>Media flows between Alice and Bob via B2BUA (Step 13, 14). </t>
       <t>STUN keepalives would be used between Alice and B2BUA (step 15) and between Bob and B2BUA (step 16) to keep NAT, Firewall bindings alive. </t>
       </list></t>
      </section>
         
      <section title="STUN interaction with DTLS-SRTP in B2BUA">
        <t> (TODO: Add reference to DTLS-STRAW draft) describes the behavior of B2BUAs when DTLS-SRTP <xref target ="RFC5764"/> is used by Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261"/> endpoints to establish a Secure Real-time Transport Protocol (SRTP) <xref target="RFC3711"/> session. When ICE is used by such endpoints, it needs to take care of the following things:</t>
      
      <t><list style="hanging">

          <t>If Aggressive nomination is used in ICE, DTLS session is setup as 
          soon as connectivity check for a media stream is complete. If a
       different candidate pair is selected after ICE conclusion, then the
       previously setup DTLS session could be re-used using session resumption as mentioned in Appendix B of <xref target="RFC5764"/>.</t>
        </list></t>

        <t><figure anchor="Figure2"
            title="INVITE with SDP having both ICE and DTLS and with a Media Plane B2BUA">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   +------+          +-------------------+             +-------+
   | Alice|          | Media Plane B2BUA |             |   Bob |
   +------+          +-------------------+             +-------+
     |(1) INVITE               |  (3)INVITE                |
     |   a=ice-ufrag1          |    a=ice-ufrag2           |
     |   a=ice-pwd1            |     a=ice-pwd2            |
     |   a=setup:actpass       |   a=setup:actpass         |
     |   a=fingerprint1        |   a= fingerprint1         | 
     |   (alice's IP/port)     |   (B2BUA's IP, port)      |   
     |(Alice's candidate list )|   (B2BUA's candidate list)|                                
     |------------------------>|  ------------------------>|
     |                         |                           |
     |    (2)  100 trying      |                           |
     | <-----------------------|                           |
     |                         | (4) 100 trying            |
     |                         | <-------------------------|
     |                         |                           |
     |                         |  (5)200 OK                |
     |                         |   a=ice-ufrag3            |
     |                         |    a=ice-pwd3             |
     |                         |   a=setup:active          |
     |                         |    a=fingerprint2         |
     |                         |  (Bob's IP, port)         |
     |                         | (Bob's candidate list)    |
     |                         | <-------------------------|
     |    (6) 200 OK           |                           |
     |    a=ice-ufrag4         |                           |
     |    a=ice-pwd4           |                           |
     |    a=setup:active       |                           |
     |    a=fingerprint2       |                           |
     |    B2BUA's address,port |                           |
     | (B2BUA's cand list1)    |                           |
     |<------------------------|                           |
     |                         |                           |
     |<----ICE Connectivity--->|                           |
     |      checks+conclusion  |<-----ICE Connectivity---->|
     |         (7)             |        checks +conclusion |
     |                         |          (8)              |
     |                         |                           |
     |    (9)    ClientHello + use_srtp on nominated pair  |
     |<------------------------|---------------------------|
     |                         |                           |
     |           (10)    ServerHello + use_srtp            |
     | ------------------------|-------------------------->|
     |                 (11)    |                           |
     |  [Certificate exchange between Alice and Bob over   | 
     |   DTLS or DTLS-SRTP channel as described in RFC5764]|  
     |                         |                           |
     |                         |                           |
     |<---------SRTP/SRTCP---->|<----SRTP/SRTCP----------->|
     |                 (12)    |      (13)                 |   
      
       ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
     
    <t>Below call flows shows a example of how a B2BUA works when both DTLS and ICE are used. In this example, the B2BUA is in media relay mode for DTLS session and passes across the fingerprint attribute in SDP from Alice to Bob without any modification.</t>
    
    <t> The above example shows a call flow where endpoints use ICE and DTLS..  The example here shows an early offer call, however the same is applicable for delay media scenarios as well.  For the sake of brevity the entire candidate list is not shown.  After ICE concludes, DTLS session is setup. DTLS session can be re-used across multiple media streams using session resumption.
DTLS-SRTP RFC also allows peers to establish multiple DTLS sessions, refer to Appendix of <xref target="RFC5764"/> for alternative approach.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="STUN Handling in B2BUA with Forked Signaling">
      <t>B2BUA's may receive multiple answers for an outbound INVITE
      due to a downstream proxy forking the INVITE to multiple
      targets. It is possible that each of these responses have
      ICE parameters signaled in the SDP. In such cases, the B2BUA SHOULD take care of doing ICE connectivity checks for each of the forked target.</t>
    </section>
</section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBA</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec.iana-considerations"
             title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
    
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5763"?>
      
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5764"?>
     
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3711"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5245"?>
      
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4086"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
        
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
        
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>
        
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7092"?>
    
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
