<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-mmusic-ice-happy-eyeballs-04"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Happy Eyeballs for ICE ">
      Happy Eyeballs Extension forICE
    </title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>
          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560103</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Prashanth Patil" initials="P." surname="Patil">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>praspati@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paal-Erik Martinsen" initials="P.E" surname="Martinsen">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Philip Pedersens vei 22</street>
          <city>Lysaker</city>
          <region>Akershus</region>
          <code>1325</code>
          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>
        <email>palmarti@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <workgroup>MMUSIC</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document provides guidelines on how to make ICE
        <xref target="RFC5245"/> conclude faster in IPv4/IPv6
        dual-stack scenarios where broken paths exists.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        There is a need to introduce more fairness in the handling of
        connectivity checks in dual-stack IPv4/IPv6 ICE
        scenarios. Section 4.1.2.1 of ICE <xref target="RFC5245"/>
        points to <xref target="RFC3484"/> for prioritizing among the
        different IP families. <xref target="RFC3484"/> is obsoleted
        by <xref target="RFC6724"/> but following the recommendations
        from the updated RFC will still lead to prioritization of IPv6
        over IPv4 with the same candidate type.
      </t>
      <t>
        As IPv6 is preferred over IPv4, recommendations made in this
        document help avoid user-noticeable delays when the IPv6 path
        is broken or excessively slow. This is achieved by making sure
        both address families are given a more "fair" treatment when
        prioritizing candidates, forming checklists or conducting
        connectivity checks.
      </t>
      <t>
        By introducing more fairness into ICE dual-stack
        implementations it will hopefully lead to better IPv6
        deployment as it will enable implementors to prioritize IPv6
        with just a small penalty for the IPv4 connectivity checks.
      </t>
      
      <section anchor="notation" title="Notational Conventions">
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
          and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          This document uses terminology defined in
          <xref target="RFC5245"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Improving ICE Dual-stack Fairness">
      <t>
        Candidates SHOULD be prioritized such that a long sequence of
        candidates belonging to the same address family be interleaved
        with candidates from the alternate IP family. For example,
        promoting IPv4 candidates in the presence of many IPv6
        addresses such that an IPv4 address candidate is always
        present after a small sequence of IPv6 addresses. This makes
        ICE connectivity checks more responsive to failures of an
        address family by reordering the candidates such that IPv6 and
        IPv4 candidates get a fair chance during connectivity checks.
      </t>  
      <t>
        An ICE agent can choose an algorithm or a technique of its
        choice to promote IPv4 candidates.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Compatibility">
      <t>
        ICE <xref target="RFC5245"/> section 4.1.2 states that the
        formula in section 4.1.2.1 SHOULD be used. Failing to do so
        may lead to ICE taking longer to converge as the checklist no
        longer will be cordinated. Therefore responsiveness of ICE
        candidate checks are improved when bothsides support
        Happy-Eyeballs. Ther might be a penaly if only one end
        supports it.
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            It is optimal when both agents support the same technique
            to promote IPv4 candidates in the candidate-list.
          </t>
          <t>
            If each happens to use a different technique to promote
            IPv4 candidates, ICE connectivity checks will be as
            responsive as the least aggressive algorithm. This is due
            to the fact that MAX/MIN logic used for calculating
            candidate-pair priority ensures that for a particular
            agent, lower-priority candidate is never used until all
            higher-priority candidates have been tried
          </t>
          <t>
            If only one agent supports Happy-Eyeballs, there is
            potentially no change in pacing of ICE connectivity checks
            and the situation is no worse than what exists today.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        None.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        STUN connectivity check using MAC computed during key
        exchanged in the signaling channel provides message integrity
        and data origin authentication as described in section 2.5 of
        <xref target="RFC5245"/> apply to this use.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        Authors would like to thank Dan Wing, Ari Keranen, Bernard
        Aboba, Martin Thomson and Jonathan Lennox for their comments
        and review.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3484"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5245"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6724"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
