<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-mmusic-ice-happy-eyeballs-07"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Happy Eyeballs for ICE ">Happy Eyeballs Extension for
    ICE</title>
    
    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>
          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560103</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Prashanth Patil" initials="P." surname="Patil">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>praspati@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Paal-Erik Martinsen" initials="P.E" surname="Martinsen">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Philip Pedersens Vei 22</street>
          <city>Lysaker</city>
          <region>Akershus</region>
          <code>1325</code>
          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>
        <email>palmarti@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <workgroup>MMUSIC</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides guidelines on how to make Interactive
      Connectivity Establishment (ICE) conclude faster in IPv4/IPv6
      dual-stack scenarios where broken paths exist.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>There is a need to introduce more fairness in the handling of
      connectivity checks for different IP address families in
      dual-stack IPv4/IPv6 ICE scenarios. Section 4.1.2.1 of ICE <xref
      target="RFC5245"/> points to <xref target="RFC3484"/> for
      prioritizing among the different IP families. <xref
      target="RFC3484"/> is obsoleted by <xref target="RFC6724"/> but
      following the recommendations from the updated RFC will lead to
      prioritization of IPv6 over IPv4 for the same candidate
      type. Due to this, connectivity checks for candidates of the
      same type (host, reflexive or relay) are sent such that an IP
      address family is completely depleted before checks on the other
      address family are started. This results in user noticeable
      setup delays if the path for the prioritized address family is
      broken.</t>

      <t>To avoid such user noticeable delays when either IPv6 or IPv4
      path is broken or excessive slow, this specification encourages
      intermingling the different address families when connectivity
      checks are conducted. Introducing IP address family fairness
      into ICE connectivity checks will lead to more sustained
      dual-stack IPv4/IPv6 deployment as users will no longer have an
      incentive to disable IPv6. The cost is a small penalty to the
      address type that otherwise would have been prioritized.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Notational Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
      in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      
        <t>This document uses terminology defined in <xref
        target="RFC5245"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Improving ICE Dual-stack Fairness">
      <t>Candidates SHOULD be prioritized such that a long sequence of
      candidates belonging to the same address family will be
      intermingled with candidates from an alternate IP family. For
      example, promoting IPv4 candidates in the presence of many IPv6
      candidates such that an IPv4 address candidate is always present
      after a small sequence of IPv6 candidates, i.e., reordering
      candidates such that both IPv6 and IPv4 candidates get a fair
      chance during the connectivity check phase. This makes ICE
      connectivity checks more responsive to broken path failures of
      an address family.</t>

      <t>An ICE agent can choose an algorithm or a technique of its
      choice to ensure that the resulting check lists have a fair
      intermingled mix of IPv4 and IPv6 address families. Modifying
      the check list directly can lead to uncoordinated local and
      remote check lists that result in ICE taking longer to complete
      or in the worst case scenario fail. The best approach is to
      modify the formula for calculating the candidate priority value
      described in ICE <xref target="RFC5245"/> section 4.1.2.1.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="compability" title="Compatibility">
      <t>ICE <xref target="RFC5245"/> section 4.1.2 states that the
      formula in section 4.1.2.1 SHOULD be used to calculate the
      candidate priority. The formula is as follows:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
     priority = (2^24)*(type preference) + 
                (2^8)*(local preference) + 
                (2^0)*(256 - component ID)
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>ICE <xref target="RFC5245"/> section 4.1.2.2 has guidelines
      for how the type preference and local preference value should be
      chosen.  Instead of having a static local preference value for
      IPv4 and IPv6 addresses, it is possible to choose this value
      dynamically in such a way that IPv4 and IPv6 address candidate
      priorities ends up intermingled within the same candidate
      type.</t>

      <t>It is also possible to dynamically change the type preference
      in such a way that IPv4 and IPv6 address candidates end up
      intermingled regardless of candidate type.  This is useful if
      there are a lot of IPv6 host candidates effectively blocking
      connectivity checks for IPv4 server reflexive candidates.</t>

      <t>The list below shows a sorted local candidate list where the
      priority is calculated in such a way that the IPv4 and IPv6
      candidates are intermingled. To allow for earlier connectivity
      checks for the IPv4 server reflexive candidates, some of the
      IPv6 host candidates was demoted. This is just an example of how
      a candidate priorities can be calculated to provide better
      fairness between IPv4 and IPv6 candidates without breaking any
      of the ICE connectivity checks.
      </t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

                  Candidate   Address Component
                    Type       Type      Id     Priority
               -------------------------------------------
               (1)  HOST       IPv6      (1)    212928947
               (2)  HOST       IPv6      (2)    2129289470
               (3)  HOST       IPv4      (1)    2129033471
               (4)  HOST       IPv4      (2)    2129033470
               (5)  HOST       IPv6      (1)    2128777471
               (6)  HOST       IPv6      (2)    2128777470
               (7)  HOST       IPv4      (1)    2128521471
               (8)  HOST       IPv4      (2)    2128521470
               (9)  HOST       IPv6      (1)    2127753471
               (10) HOST       IPv6      (2)    2127753470
               (11) SRFLX      IPv6      (1)    1693081855
               (12) SRFLX      IPv6      (2)    1693081854
               (13) SRFLX      IPv4      (1)    1692825855
               (14) SRFLX      IPv4      (2)    1692825854
               (15) HOST       IPv6      (1)    1692057855
               (16) HOST       IPv6      (2)    1692057854
               (17) RELAY      IPv6      (1)    15360255  
               (18) RELAY      IPv6      (2)    15360254  
               (19) RELAY      IPv4      (1)    15104255  
               (20) RELAY      IPv4      (2)    15104254

                SRFLX = server reflexive
  
          ]]></artwork>
      </figure></t>
      
      <t>Note that the list does not alter the component id part of
      the formula. This keeps the different components (RTP and RTCP)
      close in the list. When the checklist pair states are computed
      all pairs with the same foundation, and the the pair with the
      lowest component ID is set to Waiting.(<xref target="RFC5245"/>
      section 5.7.4. Computing States)</t>
                  
      <t>The local and remote agent can have different algorithms for
      choosing the local preference and type preference values without
      impacting the synchronization between the local and remote check
      lists.</t>

      <t>The check list is made up by candidate pairs. A candidate
      pair is two candidates paired up and given a candidate pair
      priority as described in <xref target="RFC5245"/> section
      5.7.2. Using the pair priority formula:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
     pair priority = 2^32*MIN(G,D) + 2*MAX(G,D) + (G>D?1:0)
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Where G is the candidate priority provided by the controlling
      agent and D the candidate priority provided by the controlled
      agent. This ensures that the local and remote check lists are
      coordinated.</t>

      <t>Even if the two agents have different algorithms for choosing
      the candidate priority value to get an intermingled set of IPv4
      and IPv6 candidates, the resulting checklist, that is a list
      sorted by the pair priority value, will be identical on the two
      agents.</t>

      <t>The agent that has promoted IPv4 cautiously i.e. lower IPv4
      candidate priority values compared to the other agent, will
      influence the check list the most due to (2^32*MIN(G,D)) in the
      formula.</t>

      <t>These recommendations are backward compatible with a standard
      ICE implementation. The resulting local and remote checklist
      will still be synchronized. The introduced fairness might be
      better, but not worse than what exists today</t>

    </section>

    
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>STUN connectivity check using MAC computed during key
      exchanged in the signaling channel provides message integrity
      and data origin authentication as described in section 2.5 of
      <xref target="RFC5245"/> apply to this use.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Authors would like to thank Dan Wing, Ari Keranen, Bernard
      Aboba, Martin Thomson, Jonathan Lennox and Balint Menyhart for
      their comments and review.</t>
    </section>
    
  </middle>
  
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3484"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5245"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6724"?>
      
    </references>
    
    <section title="Example Algorithm for Choosing the Local Preference">
      <t>The value space for the local preference is from 0 to 65535
      inclusive. This value space can be divided up in chunks for each
      IP address family.
      </t>
      
      <t>An IPv6 and IPv4 start priority must be given. In this
      example IPv6 starts at 60000 and IPv4 at 59000. This leaves
      enough address space to further play with the values if different
      interface priorities needs to be added. The highest value should
      be given to the address family that should be prioritized.
      </t>
      <t>
        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
       IPv6    IPv4 
       Start   Start 
65535  60k     59k    58k    57k    56k    55k                    0
+--------+------+------+------+------+------+---------------------+
|        | IPv6 | IPv4 | IPv6 | IPv4 | IPv6 |                     |
|        | (1)  |  (1) |  (2) |  (2) |  (3) |                     |
+--------+------+------+------+------+------+---------------------+
          <- N->
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>The local preference can be calculated by the given formula:
      </t>
      <t>
        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
          local_preference = S - N*2*(Cn/Cmax)
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="S:"> Address Type specific start value (IPv4 or
          IPv6 Start)</t>
          
          <t hangText="N:"> Absolute value of
          IPv6_start-IPv4_start. This ensures a positive number even
          if IPv4 is the highest priority.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText="Cn:"> Number of current candidates of a
          specific IP address type and candidate type (host, server
          reflexive or relay).
          </t>
          
          <t hangText="Cmax:"> Number of allowed consecutive
          candidates of the same IP address type.
          </t>
          
        </list>
        
      </t>
      <t>Using the values N=abs(60000-59000) and Cmax = 2 yields the
      following sorted local candidate list:
      <figure>
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
 (1)  HOST  IPv6 (1) Priority: 2129289471
 (2)  HOST  IPv6 (2) Priority: 2129289470
 (3)  HOST  IPv4 (1) Priority: 2129033471
 (4)  HOST  IPv4 (2) Priority: 2129033470
 (5)  HOST  IPv6 (1) Priority: 2128777471
 (6)  HOST  IPv6 (2) Priority: 2128777470
 (7)  HOST  IPv4 (1) Priority: 2128521471
 (8)  HOST  IPv4 (2) Priority: 2128521470
 (9)  HOST  IPv6 (1) Priority: 2128265471
 (10) HOST  IPv6 (2) Priority: 2128265470
 (11) SRFLX IPv6 (1) Priority: 1693081855
 (12) SRFLX IPv6 (2) Priority: 1693081854
 (13) SRFLX IPv4 (1) Priority: 1692825855
 (14) SRFLX IPv4 (2) Priority: 1692825854
 (15) RELAY IPv6 (1) Priority: 15360255
 (16) RELAY IPv6 (2) Priority: 15360254
 (17) RELAY IPv4 (1) Priority: 15104255
 (18) RELAY IPv4 (2) Priority: 15104254
          ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      
        The result is an even spread of IPv6 and IPv4 candidates among
        the different candidate types (host, server reflexive, relay). The
        local preference value is calculated separately for each
        candidate type.
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
